<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>London's liberty in chains discovered. And, published by Lieutenant Colonell John Lilburn, prisoner in the Tower of London, Octob. 1646.</title>
            <title>London's liberty in chains discovered. Part 1</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E359_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E359_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873640</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">130934</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 130934)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 58:E359[17] or 58:E359[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>London's liberty in chains discovered. And, published by Lieutenant Colonell John Lilburn, prisoner in the Tower of London, Octob. 1646.</title>
                  <title>London's liberty in chains discovered. Part 1</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
                  <author>Lilburne, Elizabeth. To the chosen and betrusted knights, citizens and burgesses, assembled in the high and supream court of Parliament.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Contains orders from Parliament, petitions to Parliament from various groups in London concerning their liberties, etc., as well as connecting text by Lilburne.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 was published December 18, 1646.</note>
                  <note>"To the chosen and betrusted knights, citizens and burgesses, assembled in the high and supream court of Parliament, .. The humble petition of Elizabeth Lilburne, .." (caption title, pages 65-70, leaves I1-3). [Thomason E.359[18]: similar to Wing L2077, which is a broadside].</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 2d 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:130934:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:130934:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Londons Liberty In Chains diſcovered. <hi>AND,</hi> Publiſhed by Lieutenant Golonell JOHN LILBURN, priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London, Octob.</hi> 1646.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JER. 22.15.16.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Shalt thou reign, becauſe thou cloſeſt thy ſelfe in Cedar? Did not thy Father eat and drinke, and doe judgement and juſtice, and then it was well with him?</p>
                  <p>He judged the cauſe of the poore and needy, then it was well with him: was not this to know me, ſaith the Lord?</p>
                  <p>But thine eyes and thine heart are not, but for thy covetouſneſſe, and for to ſhed innocent blood, and for oppreſſion and violence to doe it.</p>
                  <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord concerning Iehoiakim the ſonne of Ioſiah King of Iudah, They ſhall not lament for him, ſaying, Ah my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or ah my ſiſter: they ſhall not lament for him, Ah Lord, or ah his glory.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is to be obſebſerved, That the illegall election of great Miniſters and Officers for the adminiſtration and execution of Juſtice, and where the people have been and are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of this their juſt right and liberty; there have ever all act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons and practiſes of injuſtice and oppreſſions abounded: Freedome and Liberty being the onely Jewels in eſteem with the Commonalty, as a thing moſt pretious unto them, and meriting that men ſhould expoſe themſelves to all danger, for the preſervation and defence thereof againſt all tyranny and oppreſſion of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and condition ſoever.</p>
            <p>For prevention therefore of theſe miſchiefes and miſeries (which through evill government of magiſtrates by their injuſtice and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:130934:2"/>
oppreſſive practices) doe uſually fall upon Kingdomes and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And for that all lawfull powers reſide in the people, for whoſe good, welfare, and happineſſe, all government and juſt policies were ordained: And foraſmuch as that government which is violent and forced, (not reſpecting the good of the common people, but onely the will of the commander) may be properly called <hi>Tyranny:</hi> (the people having in all well ordered and conſtituted Comon-wealths, reſerved to themſelves the right and free election of the greateſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Officers of State.) Now although the tyranny whereby a City or State oppreſſeth her people, may for the preſent ſeem to be more moderate then that of one man; yet in many things it is more intollerable: And it will clearly appeare, that the miſeries wherewith a Tyrant loadeth his people, cannot bee ſo heavy as the burthens impoſed by a cruell City.</p>
            <p>Therefore all free Cities, leſt their government ſhould become a tyranny, and their Governours, through ambition and miſgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, take liberty to oppreſſe and inſlave the people to their luſts and wils; have in their firſt Conſtitutions provided, that all their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Magiſtrates ſhould be elective <hi>By Votes and Approbation</hi> of the free people of each City; and no longer to continue then a yeare, (as the <hi>Annuall Conſuls in Rome.</hi>) By which moderation of Government, the people have ſtill preſerved their ancient Liberty, enjoyed peace, honour, and accord: and have thereby avoyded thoſe calamities incident to people ſubjected to the Lawes and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Dominion of their inſulting Lords and Magiſtrates</hi> (or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters;) of all which this Honorable Citie, and Metropolis of this Kingdome, upon the firſt erecting of this Iſland into a Monarchy, or Kingdome, by that valiant, wiſe, and victorious Prince, <hi>Alfrede,</hi> who firſt freed the Land from under the <hi>Daniſh</hi> yoke and ſlavery, under which it had a long time groaned; did with the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their King, and States, then aſſembled in Parliament, for their well-being, and more peaceable good government, agree, and by a perpetuall law, ordaine; That all their Governours, and Magiſtrates, ſhould be <hi>Annuall</hi> and <hi>Elective,</hi> by the free votes of the free men of the Citie, <hi>Then,</hi> and <hi>Yet,</hi> called by the Names of <hi>Barons,</hi> and <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes of London,</hi> as appeares by their generall Charters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of their Liberties, by ſeverall Princes (before and ſince the Conqueſt) although in proceſſe of times, their Titles, and Names
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:130934:2"/>
of their Offices, bee changed; yet the power and right of election ſtill remains, and ought to continue in the body of Commonalty, and not in any particular or ſelect perſons of any Company, or Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood whatſoever. And for illuſtration, and more cleare mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation hereof, I need none other Evidence, or Proofe, then the Charter of King <hi>John,</hi> granted to the Citizens before the Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of any Company: The firſt Company that was incorporate, about the yeare of our Lord, 1327. being more then an hundred yeares after the date and grant of the aforeſaid Charter; which hath been ſince by ſundry Kings and Parliaments confirmed. Their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I have here ſet down at large; which, compared with the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, will make good your right, and Juſtifie your claime to vote <hi>In electing the Major of this Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="charter">
                        <head>The Charter.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>IOhannes Dei gratia Rex Angliae, Dom. Hiberniae, Dux Norman. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitania, &amp; Comes, Anjou. Archiepiſc. Epiſcop. Abbatis, Com. Baron. Juſtic, Vic. Prapoſitis, &amp; omnibus Ballivis fidelib. ſuic. Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, Sciatis nos conceſſiſſe, &amp; praeſenti Charta noſtra confirmaſſa Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronibus noſtris de London, quod eligant ſibi Majorem de ſeipſis ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis annis, qui nobis ſit fidelis, diſcre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>us &amp; idoneus ad regimen Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis: ita quod cum electus fuerit; nobis, vel Juſtic. noſtro, ſi praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes non fuerimus, praeſentetur, &amp; nobis Juret fidelitatem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; quod liceat eis ipſum in fine Anni amovere, &amp; alium ſubstituere ſi voluerunt vel eundem retinere. Ita tamen quod nobis oſtendatur idem vel Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic. noſtr. ſi praeſentes non fuerimus. Conceſſimus etiam eiſdem Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronibus noſtris, &amp; hac Charta noſtra confirmavimus quod habeant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; in pace quiete &amp; integre omnes libertates ſuas quibus hactenus uſi ſunt, tam in Civitate quam extra tam in terris quam aquis, &amp; omnibus aliis locis. Salva nobis Chamblengeria noſtra. Quare vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus &amp; firmiter praecipimus quod praedicti Barones noſtri Civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis noſtrae London eligant ſibi Majorem ſingulis Annis de ſeipſis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto modo: &amp; quod omnes praedictas <hi>Libertates,</hi> &amp;c. bene &amp; in pace ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant ſicut praedict. &amp;c. Teſtibus, &amp;c. Anno regni decimo ſexto.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="4" facs="tcp:130934:3"/>
                           <hi>JOHN</hi> by the grace of God, King of <hi>England,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy, Aquitain,</hi> and Earl of <hi>Anjeou,</hi> To his Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Earls, Barons, Juſtices, Sheriffes, Stewards, and all his Bayliffes, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subjects greeting; Know ye, rhat We have granted, and by this preſent <hi>Charter,</hi> have confirmed to our Barons of <hi>London,</hi> That they may chuſe to themſelves every year a Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of themſelves, who is faithfull to Us, being diſcreet and fit for government of the City. So that when he ſhall be choſen, he be preſented to Vs, or to Our Juſtice, if We be not preſent, and ſwear to Us fidelity, and that it may be lawfull for them at the end of the Year, to remove him, and and appoint another, or retain him, if they pleaſe; yet ſo, as the ſame be ſhewed to Us, or to Our Juſtice, if Wee bee not preſent. Moreover. We have granted to Our ſaid Barons, and by this Our Charter have confirmed, that they may wel, and in peace quietly and fully have and enjoy all the Liberties which hitherto they have uſed, as well in the City as without: in the Land as in the Waters, and in all other places, ſaving to Us Our <hi>Chamberiege;</hi> Wherefore We will and firmly command, that Our ſaid Barons of Our City of <hi>London,</hi> may yearly elect a Major of themſelves, after the aforeſaid manner, and have and enjoy, well and in peace, wholly and fully, all their ſaid Liberties, with all things appertaining to the ſame afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; Witneſſe, &amp;c. in the 16. Year of Our Raign.</p>
                        <p>Wherein is fit to be obſerved. 1. That all the Free-men of <hi>London</hi> be all and every of them Barons, being ſo intituled and ordained by the Kings Grant or Charter. 2. That every of them hath his free Vote in the election of their Major. 3. That they have liberty to chuſe any Baron or Burgeſſe from amongſt themſelves, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction or reference to any particular perſon or perſons, or to any other Fraternities of Aldermen, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-Councell men, or any other particular Gown or Livery-men only; ſo as he be faithfull, diſcreet, and ſuch as they judge fit to govern. 4. That no Major may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in office above one year, without a new Election. 5. That Aldermen were likewiſe eligible by the Commonalty, and but to continue for the yeare, <hi>Patent</hi> 22. <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. <hi>No:</hi> 2. <hi>Cook</hi> 2. <hi>Part Inſtitutions, fol.</hi> 253. 6. Sheriffes are only eligible by the Barons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:130934:3"/>
or Burgeſſes of the City, as appeareth by by the Charter of <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. made in the 11. Year of his Raign, confirmed after by <hi>Henry</hi> the 5. <hi>Charta de</hi> 2. <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>No.</hi> 11. But of late yeares the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and Common-Councell of this City, by their power and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, have invaded your rights and juſt priviledges, and contrary to the fundamental Law of the Land, &amp; the antient cuſtoms of the City, moſt injuriouſly have betrayed the truſt repoſed in them: ſpoiled you of your Liberties: taken upon them (of themſelves, with ſome ſelected Companies) without the free vote, the reſt of the Barons or free Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes (the Commonalty) of this City, the ſole Power &amp; Government of the City, changing and altering your Lawes and Cuſtomes at their pleaſure, and chuſing of Majors and Sheriffes, ſuch, and whom they pleaſed, hindering and prohibiting all others (who ever had the like equall right and intereſt with them) to have their Votes in the choiſe and election of the Major and Sheriffes. Whence have enſued many calamities and miſeries, even to the indangering of the utter over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and deſolation of this moſt famous and honourable City of <hi>Europe,</hi> being wholly disfranchiſed of thoſe liberties, and immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which even the meaneſt Burrough or Corporation in <hi>England</hi> now enjoyeth.</p>
                        <p>Hence, by their craft and policy, have ſo many Monopolies and Pattents under pretext of publike good, been brought in, and ſet up to the ruining of thouſands, and great decay of Trade &amp; Traffique, bringing in and countenancing of Arbitrary Lawes, and unlimited Power and Government, and whereby <hi>Tyrannie, Injuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> have without controle been exerciſed and practiſed by theſe your late Governours and Rulers, as well as by thoſe your former Governours and Magiſtrates, not by the Commonalty.</p>
                        <p>Were not the Land-Money, Ship-money (and many other illegall Taxes and Impoſitions) with rigour and force exacted of you Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens by theſe your illegall Governours? Were not many of you free Barons of this City (for refuſing to pay thoſe exactions, and to part with your eſtates by ſuch illegall tyrannous courſes) impriſoned by theſe your Governours (thus illegally forced upon you without your own free Election?) Were not the cruell Edicts, and bloudy tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Decree of the <hi>Star-Chamber, High Commiſſion,</hi> and <hi>Councell-Table,</hi> withall readineſſe in a compulſive Torrent executed? Nay, to reckon up in particular, the ſeverall cruelties, exactions, oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:130934:4"/>
inſolencies, violencies, and the illegall practiſes and proceedings of theſe your Magiſtrates, and their ſubordinate Miniſters; would require a particular Tractate, which I rather deſire might be buried in Oblivion, by a timely reſtauration of you to your antient and juſt freedomes in electing your own Officers. But if ſtill you be denied Juſtice, and may not enjoy your due and accuſtomed priviledges; I ſhall be occaſioned to remonſtrate at large, and in particular, ſet forth your ſeverall heavy burthens, harſh dealings, great grievances, and ſeverall incroachments upon your Franchiſes: how, and by whom your Rights and Liberties have been invaded: and how you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved, that were, and are (or at leaſt of Right ought to be) free Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes and Barons, but now captivated to the Lawes, covetous Luſts, and the Arbitrarie unlimitted power and dominion of your illegal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imperious lording Magiſtrates.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, for the preſent, I will inſiſt only upon the manner of the election of your now new Lord Major: The Narrative whereof will fully diſcover, how much the Barons of this City ſuffer, and that by their long forbearance, or rather neglect, to own and claime their juſt priviledges and immunities (if they ſtoutly ſtand not up) and reſolve to be no longer robbed and ſpoyled of their Birth-right and Inheritance; They are, and wil be then in danger to be reduced into a condition worſe then ever any of your Progenitors, were, under the <hi>Baſtard Norman Bondage.</hi> For indeed, you Citizens are but free-men in name, as in truth this your giving up your ſelves to the power and government of men, without your free and publike choice and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, demonſtrates: and therefore (truly) you can be accompted none other then meer ſlaves to your thus elected Governour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, as the reſt of the whole Nation is become, unto Lawyers, Attornies, Clerks, Solicitors, and cruell Jaylors, and ſuch inſtruments of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by whom the peace and flouriſhing State of this Kingdome is quite devoured and the people wholly inſlaved to their wills; for truth hereof, I appeal to all the Inhabitants of every countie through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Kingdome, whoſe eſtates, purſes, and perſons, have for theſe many ſcore of years groaned under the inhumane burden thereof; all which, is farther demonſtrated unto us all, the Inhabitants of this Land, by the (ſtill continued) frequent, unjuſt, and illegall Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your fellow-Citizens, and all the free Commoners of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to the ſeverall murthering-houſes (ſtiled Priſons) in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:130934:4"/>
aboundnig in cruelty, murther, and oppreſſion: being moſt wickedly and powerfully countenanced and ſupported by their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Adherents.</p>
                        <p>I have ſhewed you, how by right, the meaneſt Baron of this City of <hi>London</hi> (by their Charter) hath as good right to have his vote in the Election of the new Major, and other the ſubordinate Officers, as the Lord Major, or any Aldermen (for the time being) with their Golden Chaines. Notwithſtanding, this undoubted Right be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged; yet is it denied to the people upon bare ſurmiſes, and vain pretences of danger, by tumults and diſorder, if the ſame ſhould be yeelded unto, which in truth is, but a poor allegation, and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous excuſe: The vanity and weakneſſe whereof, muſt needes be apparent to any who is <hi>impartiall,</hi> and not carryed aſide with deſire of Rule, through Ambition, and blinded with affection, or beaſtly beſotted, and againſt Nature and Reaſon, loving Bondage more then Liberty. For what miſchief (I pray you) do we find, or have we ever heard of in any Town, City, or Corporation, (where the Citizens have, and enjoy this freedome) of any diſorder or tumults that have grown thence?</p>
                        <p>Were not the Sheriffes (till now of late) ever choſen by the free-holders in full County? &amp; yet we find not that chuſing to have bin complained of but rather (only) by Prerogative Power taken away to defrauding the people of their free choice due &amp; of right belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them, by the great <hi>Charter</hi> of the Kingdom. And how are the Commons and Burgeſſes now aſſembled in that High Court of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> elected? Whether by the Sheriffe, and ſome few ſelected <hi>Grandees</hi> of each County, or by the Majority of voyces of all &amp; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Free-holders that will appear, &amp; give their votes upon the day aſſigned by Proclamation, if our great Senators come in place, and be choſen by the generall and free voyce of all, and not of a few (like ſome) which hath been the right manner of Election from the firſt eſtabliſhment of this Kingdome, and ſo hath continued to this day, being conceived to be the beſt forme of Government, and ſo hath been found to be by approved experience? For, did <hi>Rome</hi> ever ſo flouriſh, as when, not any thing was done but by the Senate and People there? But of this, expect a larger Diſcourſe.</p>
                        <p>I pray you, whence have we fetched this new wiſdome? Surely, not from above, but beneath; it being none other then Satanicall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:130934:5"/>
pride in thus deſpiſing their fellowes, and free Commoners. For theſe can be of no other ſpirit, but ſuch as affect <hi>Tyranny, Injuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion:</hi> And being thus, is it not then a lawleſſe Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>and ſo, not of God, but of the Divell?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But let us now ſay ſomewhat of the election of the Maior upon the 29. of <hi>September,</hi> 1646. the day aſſigned for electing the Maior of <hi>London;</hi> at which time Mr <hi>Wanſie,</hi> a Citizen and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>London,</hi> came to the Guild-Hall, <hi>London,</hi> the place appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for electing the Lord Maior for the yeare enſuing the doore of the Hall being kept ſhut) the Marſhal of <hi>London,</hi> who was with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, ſtanding with ſtaves, to keep the doore: But Mr. <hi>Wanſie,</hi> with divers other Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> deſired, that they might have liberty to goe into the Hall; telling them, that they came with intent to paſſe their free votes in electing the new Lord Maior. But could not by any meanes obtain liberty to enter the Hall, (although by them earneſtly deſired) but were kept out forcibly with Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts, Bills, and Staves, upon a ſpeciall command of the now Lord Maior, <hi>Thomas Adams:</hi> Whereupon the ſaid Citizens having fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Proteſt, (which they intended to deliver in the open Court) the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wanſie</hi> having the ſaid Proteſt in his hand, and reading it to the reſt of the Citizens there preſent; the ſaid Marſhall thereupon with force, and much violence, laid hold on him (with the ſaid proteſt in his hand) and dragged him into the Guild-Hall, and kept him there as a priſoner for the ſpace of an houre, until the Lord Maior, and Aldermen came from the Sermon: and then hee was brought before the Lord Maior, and Court of Aldermen; who there examined him ſtrictly about the ſaid Proteſt; demanding where he had it, and who delivered it to him. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> they all threatned him very violently, that they would ſend him to <hi>New</hi>-gate. But he anſwered, That he knew not the framer of it, nor him that delivered the ſaid proteſt unto him: and then alſo affirming, that he and the reſt of the Citizens, intended to have ſubſcribed it, and then to have delivered it unto h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s Lordſhip, and the reſt of the Court. But the ſaid Proteſtation was derained from him. And he thereupon diſmiſſed for the preſent, with ingagement by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that he would attend his Lordſhip the day following. But for more aſſurance, his Lordſhip ſent an Officer for him (as for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent.) Upon whoſe appearing before the Lord Maior, the ſaid
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:130934:5"/>
ſaid Marſhall made a great complaint againſt the ſaid M. <hi>Wanſie,</hi> for ſaying that he would queſtion him the ſaid Marſhall for abuſing him, as aforeſaid, being very earneſt with his Lordſhip to have him committed. But the Lord Maior and ſome of the Aldermen for that time, diſmiſſed and let him goe.</p>
                        <p>Thus you may ſee how imperious this Marſhal is (being none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a meere vaſſall or ſervant unto the Citizens of <hi>London</hi>) ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing and expreſſing his diſaffection to all honeſt and good men, in the higheſt nature.</p>
                        <p>After the thus election of the Lord Maior, the Livery men depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and the Court not riſen, the Hall doore then being opened; the Lord Maior, <hi>Thomas Adams,</hi> gve command to the Conſtables and Halbert-men then ſtanding at the doore, that they ſhould take care that no Cloak-men ſhould come in; fearing, as it is conceived, leſt the Citizens ſhould come in, and proteſt againſt that unjuſt and undue election of the new Lord Maior.</p>
                        <p>This briefe relation, that made unto you, may bee a ſufficient diſcovery of the intentions and ſiniſter ends of your great <hi>Maſters,</hi> to continue you ſtill under an enforced ſlavery and ſubjection, who eſteeming you no other then as objects, &amp; as unworthy to have any thing to do in the choyce of your own <hi>Officers,</hi> withholding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you your <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Franchiſes,</hi> the more to blind you, and keep you in ignorance, that they may the better <hi>carry on their deſignes</hi> againſt you, for the continuance of your <hi>thraldome,</hi> and to hold your necks under their yoak.</p>
                        <p>The very relation of the bad uſage of M. <hi>Wanfie,</hi> with the manner of the election of the <hi>Maior,</hi> compared with your Claim of Right, and Proteſtation againſt the ſame, is ſufficient to ſhew &amp; plainly ſet forth the illegality therof, to which you cannot ſubmit, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying your own <hi>Liberty.</hi> Your <hi>Proteſtation</hi> being in my hand, I held it my duty no longer to conceal it: but for your common good to publiſh the ſame, hoping, that as you have freely fought for your <hi>Liberties,</hi> ſworn to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> your <hi>Liberties,</hi> and largely contributed to the State to inable them to protect you in your <hi>Liberties:</hi> ſo you will not ſit ſtill, and paſſe by this injury and indignity of thoſe that would and doe make themſelves Lords and Maſters over you, by violence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> wrong. But inſtantly adhere to your <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> conclude the claime of your right, and with courage and reſolution,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:130934:6"/>
maintain and preſerve your iuſt and undeniable Liberties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which are thus unjuſtly extorted, and kept from you by fraud and force, leſt it be ſaid in after ages; <hi>Theſe were the men, theſe were the Fathers that durſt not, would not, own their Liberties and Rights: Theſe were the men, who when a free Parliament were ſitting, ſubjected them, and their Poſterity to voluntary ſlavery.</hi> If you neglect this opportunity, and advantage offered you, for the regai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your Liberties, and recovery of your Birth-right (the Law;) the loſſe will be irrepayable, irrecoverable, bringing with it certain ruine, &amp; unavoidable vaſſalage upon you, and your whole City; yea, though I am not a Citizen, yet no ſtranger, nor forreigner, but a free-man of <hi>England,</hi> who hath freely hazarded all, for the recovery of the common Liberty, and my Countries freedome; and it is no ſmall griefe unto me; yea, it lyes more heavy upon me, then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my troubles undergone, to ſee our <hi>Nationall and Fundamentall Lawes, Rights, and Priviledges, thus trodden under foot,</hi> even by thoſe, by whoſe endeavours we expected a reſtauration of the ſame. Oh! the unexpreſſable miſery, and beſotted condition poſſeſſing this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we ſhould be ſo regardleſſe of our ſelves and Poſterity, as thus in, and by cowardly ſilence, to betray our ſelves, and to beget Children, to live and remain (by our meanes) <hi>Bond-men,</hi> and <hi>Bond-women;</hi> yea, <hi>Slaves.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Look but upon your induſtrious Neighbour-Nation, the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> how for a long time, under faire and colourable pretences; <hi>(As Conformity, and Religion,)</hi> they were ſpoyled of their Lives, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Eſtates. But at the length, they diſcovered the cunning and crafty dealings and deviſes of the Biſhops, and their Clergie, whom the Spaniard promoted, and uſed as his Inſtruments, by whom he intended to bring thoſe Countries under the power of his Soveraignty, and cruell will. Theſe your Neighbours were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to knit themſelves together by Bond and Oath, to ſtand up for their common Liberties, and Countries ſafety, leaning every man (in matters of Religion) according to that common Principle, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio ſuadenda non cogenda,</hi> Religion may be perſwaded, not for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced; &amp; the good ſucceſſe they have had therein, and tranquility and ſecurity they thereby enjoy; may be great incouragement to us, not to deſpaire of the recovery of our Native, and juſt Freedoms, and by the like meanes to put an end to theſe our troubles, &amp; unnatural op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:130934:6"/>
if we will but tread in the ſame ſteps, each one labouring in his place to preſerve the common Liberties and Lawes of the Kingdome, which makes us indeed true free-men, without ſeeking, or endeavouring to Lord it thus (as now we do) one over anothers faith; your Brethren, together with you, and all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> have an equall intereſt, and property in the Law, being all of us free-born <hi>Engliſh-men.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Therefore look about you, and be no longer deluded to be by a meer ſhadow of greatneſſe and flattery, fooled into ſlavery; But ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> endeavour to preſerve, or rather recover your loſt Liberties, which under conformity, and other ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and gloſſes, you have been long deprived of: Till when, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not any Juſtice or Right to be done unto you: For, it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for thoſe that have reduced you to this ſlavery, to degenerate ſo far from themſelves, as to maintain or give you any aſſiſtance or countenance, in ſtanding for liberty, untill they lay down their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Functions, which they all this time have unjuſtly uſurped, and intruded themſelves into. I will forbear to inſiſt further upon this matter for the preſent, being ready and willing, if any ſhould preſume to queſtion the Citizens juſt rights, in the election of their Major; upon the perill of my head, and forfeiture of my life (if I be called thereunto, and may have a juſt and equall hearing) to prove and maintain, <hi>That it is the juſt and due Right and Liberty, for any free Citixen and Baron to give his vote in the election of the Major, and Sheriffes, and other the publike Officers: the ſame being grounded upon the Law of God and Nations, and agreeable, as well with the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Lawes of this Kingdome, and Cuſtomes of this City, as by the Charter and Acts of Parliament (yet unrepealed,) is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But one thing I cannot paſſe by (which may cauſe ſome ſcruples) which is thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </p>
                        <p>By the words <hi>(Barons of London)</hi> mentioned in King <hi>John</hi> his <hi>Charter,</hi> Whether, all, or but ſome ſpeciall Citizens of note, are to be underſtood; to be the Electors of the Major and Sheriffes of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That all and every Citizen is there meant and implyed; The very words of the <hi>Charter</hi> it ſelf clearly manifeſt: For, the Liberties
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:130934:7"/>
there granted by the <hi>Charter,</hi> are to them all as <hi>Barons,</hi> and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, nor to any other particular perſons of any Society: Yet the ſame may be farther cleared, thus in that before the Conqueſt; all Free-holders of this Kingdome, (as well as in <hi>Scotland,</hi> are yet to this day) were called <hi>Barons;</hi> and therefore ſaith, <hi>Lamb. fol</hi> 128. and 136. <hi>Court-Baron is ſo called,</hi> becauſe amongſt the Laws of King <hi>Edward the Confeſſour,</hi> it is ſaid thus, <hi>Barones vero qui ſuam habent Curiam de ſuis hominibus,</hi> &amp;c. Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are thoſe who have their Court for their Tenants or men. And this Juriſdiction hath every Free-holder, according to <hi>Mirrour,</hi> C. 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>un, free Tenant uſe juriſdiction ordinary:</hi> every Free-holder hath this ordinary ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction; and the name <hi>Baron</hi> in the eye of the Law hath relation to Free-holders, ſaith Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> 1. <hi>Part, Inſtitut. fol.</hi> 58. and in very antient Charters and Records, ſaith he, The Barons of <hi>London,</hi> and the Barons of the Cinque-Ports, doe ſignifie, the Free-men of <hi>London,</hi> and the Free-men of the Cinque-Ports, <hi>Cook ibid.</hi> All which, I deſire may be taken into due conſideration: which, as I writ the <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> ſo this I have publiſhed for the good of this famous City, and for the benefit of all the Barons thereof; and if you will own this your right, and not ſuffer your ſelves to be brought into voluntary ſervitude; I ſhall be encouraged to make a farther diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Priviledges and juſt Rights, now unjuſtly detained, and holden from you.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>By the Contriver of the Citizens Proteſtation, here following.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="protestation">
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:130934:7"/>
                        <head>The Copy of the Proteſtation made by the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> the 29. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1646.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The right and claime of the Free-men Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and Commonalty of the famous and moſt antient City of <hi>London,</hi> for their Votes in the election of their great and higheſt Officer, the Lord Major, &amp;c. With their <hi>Proteſtation</hi> againſt the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch, who ſhall be elected Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jors, as illegall and deſtructive to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Priviledges of this City, if in caſe the Commonalty, and Freemen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or any of them, be denied, and not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to have their Votes in the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>WHereas this City hath had, and enjoyed before, and ſince the Conqueſt, many great and notable Franchiſes, Cuſtome, and Priviledges, often and ſundry times confirmed, as well by the Laws
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:130934:8"/>
and Statutes made in the ſeverall Parliaments, as by the ſeveral Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Kings and Queens of this Realme appeareth; amongſt which, it hath been an antient and laudable cuſtome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (Time out of mind) for all, and every the Free-men and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> in the <hi>annuall</hi> elections of the Majors thereof, to have their votes, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they had,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Porte Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve,</hi> ſignifieth the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; ſafe Keeper of the City, or Town gates.</note> in the election of their <hi>Porte Graves.</hi> In whoſe place and office, the Major ſucceeded; as appeareth by the Charter of King <hi>John,</hi> granted in the ſixteenth yeare of his Raigne, where hee granteth to the Citizens, Liberty and Authority to chuſe yearly a Major out of themſelves, <hi>Cook</hi> the 4. Part, <hi>Inſtitut. fol.</hi> 253. Printed by Authority of this preſent Parliament.</p>
                        <p>Which Cuſtome, of Election of Majors, by majority of voyces of the Free-men and Commoners of the City, agreeth with the Fundamentall Law of this Kingdome, and the manner of election of Majors, in all other the Cities and Burroughs of this Realme as Coroners, were, and are choſen in full County, by the Free-holders of each County, <hi>Inter leges Edward. Sanct. Chap. Lambert, folio</hi> 136. <hi>Artic. ſuper. Charta, chap.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Major is Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner within the City of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now, foraſmuch as we be Free-men, and Commoners, and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes of this City, and ſo have right, and ought to have our Votes in the election of the Major; Do hereby claime, and demand, as our Right, Cuſtome, and Priviledge, to vote in the election of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Major to be choſen; and doe likewiſe hereby ſignifie, That for the ſame end wee are come hither, to give our free votes in elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Major for the enſuing year, if we may freely, without moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, diſturbance, and interruption, doe the ſame, according to the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the 5. <hi>chap.</hi> the 9. of <hi>Edward</hi> the 2. 14. The words whereof are theſe;</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And for that Elections ought to be free;</hi> it is ordained, upon pain of great forfeiture, That no Noble man, or other, by force of Armes, neither through malice or menacies, ſhal hinder to make free Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in Counties, Vniverſities, Cities, Corporations, and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Cook</hi> 2. <hi>Part, Inſtit. fol.</hi> 169.</p>
                        <p>And foraſmuch, as all the due, juſt, and accuſtomed Priviledges, Franchiſes, Liberties, and Immunities of this City, are confirmed by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:130934:8"/>
this preſent <hi>Parliament, The Petition of Right,</hi> And <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the great Charter of Liberties, where it is ſaid, That the City of <hi>London</hi> ſhall have and enjoy all its antient Liberties, and Cuſtomes, <hi>Mag. Chart. chap.</hi> 9. and the 28. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>E.</hi> 1.</p>
                        <p>And although it may ſeeme, by reaſon of ſome undue elections of late yeares made, through uſurpation of ſome few, who by power and menacies, hindering the free Elections, not ſuffering us the Free-men and Commoners to give our votes upon chuſing and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Majors to be a Barre, let, or hinderance to this our preſent voting; yet the ſame doth nothing at all prejudice our Rights, but rather aggravates the wrong done unto us: For there is a benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Statute (yet unrepealed) made for the ſtrengthening and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our Liberties and Rights, which no other Corporation hath that we know of; Whereby it is enacted, That the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> ſhall enjoy all their whole Liberties whatſoever, with this clauſe, <hi>Licet uſi vel abuſi fuerunt,</hi> Although they have not uſed or abuſed the ſame, and notwithſtanding any Statute to the contrary, <hi>Parl. Rot. R.</hi> 2. <hi>N.</hi> 37.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, if we may not be admitted, being Free-men and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>London,</hi> to enjoy our due and accuſtomed Priviledges and Liberties, to have and give our free votes in the election of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, we being by <hi>Parliament</hi> injoyned, and by Oath and Proteſtation bound, to our uttermoſt power, to defend and preſerve the lawfull Rights and Liberties of the People; Doe declare and proteſt againſt all ſuch who ſhall any-wiſe hinder us, or any of us, in a free way, to vote in the electing of the ſaid Major; as oppugnors and violators of the Lawes and Liberties of the Kingdome, <hi>and deſtroyers of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of this antient Metropolitan City,</hi> and ſhall by all lawfull wayes and meanes, labour to bring them to condigne puniſhment, for ſuch their offences.</p>
                        <p>And wee doe hereby declare, and proteſt againſt the Major, ſo unduly and illegally elected, being choſen without our free Votes and conſents, who have right, and are come hither to give in our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:130934:9"/>
free votes, if wee might have freely, peaceably, and without let or trouble done the ſame, alwayes acknowledging our obedience, and ſhall bee ready, with all alacrity and cheerfulneſſe to manifeſt the ſame, to our lawfull Magiſtracie duly elected, in all their juſt Commands.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>LONDON.</hi>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="postscript">
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:130934:9"/>
                        <head>A <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> written by Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> Priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> Octob. <hi>1646.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THE omnipotent, glorious, and wiſe God, creating man for his own praiſe; made him more glorious then all the reſt of his Creatures that he placed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth: creating him in his own Image, (which principally conſiſted in his reaſon and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) and made him Lord over the earth, and all the things therein contained, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26, 27, 28, 29. and <hi>chap.</hi> 5.1. and 9.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10; But made him not Lord, or gave him dominion over the individuals of Mankind, no further then by free conſent, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, by giving up their power, each to other, for their better being; ſo that originally, he gave no Lordſhip, nor Soveraignty, to any of <hi>Adams Poſterity,</hi> by Will, and Prerogative, to rule over his Brethren-Men, but ingraved by nature in the ſoule of Man, this goulden and everlaſting principle, to doe to another, as the would have another to do to him; but man by his tranſgreſſion, falling from his perfection of reaſon (that Image in which God created him, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10.) became tyrannicall, and beaſtly in his principles and actions; the effect of which, we ſee in <hi>Caines</hi> ſlaying of <hi>Abel;</hi> for which he was accurſed of God, and all things hee went about, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.8, 10, 11, 12. but God taking mercy of Mankind in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and not executing the fulneſſe of his wrath, in the 9. of <hi>Gen.</hi> to revenge that beaſtlineſſe, bloody, revengfull, and devouring temper of Spirit, that, by the fall, had now entred into the Spirits of all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:130934:10"/>
Mankind; inſtitutes a perpetuall, morall, unchangeable, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Law; that is to ſay, <hi>That whoſoever he was, that would be ſo beaſtly, beariſh, and Woolviſh, as to fall upon his neighbour, brother, or friend, and to do vnto him that, which he would not he ſhould do to him, by taking away his life and blood from him; God ordaines, and expreſly ſaith he ſhall loſe his life without mercy or compaſſion for ſo doing, verſ.</hi> 5.6. Yea, and afterwards, when he chuſeth unto himſelf <hi>Iſrael,</hi> out of all the Nations of the world to be his peculiar people, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.15, 16, 17, 18. ordaines this for a ſtanding Law amongſt them; <hi>Yee ſhall do no unrighteouſneſſe in judgment; thou ſhalt not reſpect the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty; but in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhalt thou judge thy Neighbour. Thou ſhalt not go up and down as a Tale-bearer amongſt thy people; neither ſhalt thou ſtand againſt the bloud of thy neighbour: I am the Lord. Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy heart: thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy neighbour, and not ſuffer ſinne upon him. Thou ſhalt not avenge, nor bear any grudge againſt the Children of thy People; but thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelfe: I am the Lord.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And when the fulneſſe of time was come, that Chriſt the Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and Repairer of mans loſſe and fall, ſhould come and preach Righteouſneſſe &amp; Juſtice to the world; <hi>He ſaith, it is the Law, &amp; the Prophets, that whatſoever we would that men ſhould do to us, that wee ſhould do to them,</hi> Matth. 7.12. Luke 6.31. Yea, and further ſaith, <hi>That as it is the great Commandement, that we ſhould love</hi> (our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Creator, and Preſerver) <hi>the Lord our God with all our hearts, and all our ſoules, and with all our minds;</hi> ſo the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is like unto it, is, <hi>That we ſhould love our neighbours as our ſelves;</hi> and on theſe two, ſaith <hi>hee, hang all the Law and the Prophets:</hi> So that by this, it is cleerly evident, that Religion, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; or the knowledge of Chriſt, doth not deſtroy morality, civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, juſtice, and right reaſon; but rather reſtores it to its firſt perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, beauty, ſplendor, and glory: and therefore the Apoſtle exhorts Saints and Believers, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>Not to walk as other Gentiles do, in the vanity of their mind, having their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding darkened, being alienated from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſſe of their heart. Who being paſt feeling; have given themſelvs over to laſciviouſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſſe, to work all uncleanneſſe with greedineſſe.</hi> But (ſaith the Apoſtle to all that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:130934:10"/>
love Chriſt,) <hi>Ye have not ſo learned Chriſt: If ſo be ye have heard him, and have been taught by him, as the truth is in Jeſus. That ye put off, concerning the former converſation, the old man; which is corrupt, according to the deceitfull luſts: And be renewed in the Spirit of your mind. And that ye put on that new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe;</hi> and excellent to this purpoſe, is that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Col</hi> 3.7, 8. where ſpeaking of, and to thoſe that have put off the old man, with his deeds; and have put on the new man, which (ſaith he) is <hi>renewed in knowledge, after the Image of him that created him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And therefore the ſame Apoſtle layeth down his exhortation at large, and declareth, it is not only the duty of the Saints, to doe good each unto other, but <hi>as much as in them lyes, to doe good unto all the Sons of Adam;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>as we have therefore opportunity, let us do good unto</hi> all men; <hi>eſpecially, unto them, who are of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold of Faith.</hi> But the greateſt good that I know of, that any man can do unto the Sons of Men beſides the diſcovery of the knowledge of Chriſt, and the benefits and priviledges that are to be injoyed by him; is, rationally to diſcover the privilege, that is, the Right, Due, and Propriety of all the Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> as men: that ſo they may not live in beaſtlineſſe, by devouring one another: and not onely ſo, but alſo to ſtand for, and maintain thoſe Rights and Priviledges in any Kingdome, or Nation, whereſoever they are in any meaſure eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed: that ſo the truſted, made great and potent, by a power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon them; may not there-with (as is too commonly ſeene) Lord it, domineer over, and deſtroy by their Prerogative-will and pleaſure, the Betruſters: yea, and alſo to maintain the liberties and priviledges eſtabliſhed in a Land, by Law, againſt the incroaching uſurpations of ſome great and mighty <hi>Nimrods</hi> of the world, made ſo by wayes and meanes, more immediatly and properly flowing from the Divell, then God: and by their falſe-aſſumed incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power, tyrant-like tread under their feet, all juſt, and innocent perſons: and protect, defend, and countenance none but thoſe, that will comply, applaud, and aſſiſt them, in their brutiſh, woolviſh, and tyrant-like proceedings: which practiſes are contrary to the very end of Government, and Magiſtracy; as is largly declared by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Rom. 13.3, 4. where he plainly ſaith, <hi>Rulers are not</hi> (no nor ought not to be) <hi>a terrour to good workes, but to the evill: wilt thou
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:130934:11"/>
then not be afraid of the power? Do that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame. For he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good: But if thou do that which is evill, be afraid, for he beareth not the ſword in vain; for he is the Minister of God, a Revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evill, but not upon him that doth good.</hi> The knowledge of which, in ſome meaſure, in my own ſoule, hath been the true ground, that conſcienciouſly made me out of duty to my ſelfe, and neighbours, and obedience to God; ſtand againſt, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my ſelf againſt the Biſhops, and with reſolution ſo often ſince, in the middeſt of many deaths; hazard my life for my liberties, and the lawes, liberties, and rights of all the people of this Land, &amp; which is the only principle that now carryes me on in oppoſition againſt the Lords: unto whom, as ſo many men, I have and muſt confeſſe, I am ten times more oblieged, for my own particular, than to the houſe of Commons it ſelf, having found at their hands ſeveral times cordiall and ſpeedy Juſtice, which I never enjoyed from the Houſe of Commons in my life; although I have waited upon them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, theſe ſix years, and followed them as cloſe as any man (I think) in <hi>England:</hi> and I dare ſafely ſay it, without vain or lying boaſting; for theſe nine or ten years together, I have been as ſerviceable to the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> in my place and condition, as any one man whatſoever that ſits in that houſe; though I have been as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully dealt with by them, as ever man in <hi>England</hi> was: yet I ſay, when the Lords forced me to conteſt with them, which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, I was as unwilling to do, as I was to run my head againſt the wall, the which I told unto one of themſelves; yet I ſay, before I would have parted with my reaſon and underſtanding, and ſo have defaced, obliterated, and annihilated, as much as in me lay, the Image that God created me in, (and which Chriſt by communicating of himſelf to me; hath reſtored, confirmed, and inlarged) and degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the habit of a beaſt, (which all ſlaves that live in the World without a rationall and juſt Law are in) by parting with, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying my native, naturall, juſt liberties, which the fundamentall lawes of this Land give me; I will part with my very heart-blood firſt; yea, and if I had a thouſand lives, they ſhould all go, before I will part with my juſt liberties, either to them, or any power on earth, what ever it be, that dare aſſume unto themſelves ſo much ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and ſatanicall pride as to go about it, or endeavour it. And it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:130934:11"/>
is this very principle that now engageth to write this <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> to beget a Conteſt with the Prerogative-men of <hi>London, Englands</hi> mighty <hi>Nimrods,</hi> who haue inſlaved not only this City, but beene ſtrong Inſtruments from time to time, to doe the ſame to the whole Land. And the preſent ground of my putting pen to paper at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ariſeth from this enſuing: The day the laſt Lord Major was ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; <hi>It ſeemes, Major Wanſie, a Watch-maker in Cornhill, (a man that in theſe late wars, hath freely and gallantly adventured his life for the preſervation of the preſent Parliament, and Englands Liberties) and ſome other free Citizens,</hi> commonly by the Prerogative-men of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi>Cloak-men;</hi> intended to have clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med their right, to give their Vote in the election of the Lord Major, as by Law, and the Charters of <hi>London,</hi> every free-man therof ought to do; as alſo, in both the Sheriffes, &amp;c. And in caſe the prerogative- L. Major <hi>Adams,</hi> and the prerogative-Aldermen his Brethren, would not permit them; They then intended, to deliver in a Proteſt in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; the Copy of which Proteſt within a day or two after, I ſaw and read, and not before: and underſtanding how baſely Major <hi>VVanſey</hi> was uſed by the Marſhall of <hi>London,</hi> and of my Lord Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jors prerogative-Maſtives; and how that contrary to Law, Guild-Hall Gate was guarded with armed men, which rendered the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in no ſence to be free, as all elections of all publike Officers ought to be; and reading the Proteſt over, the reaſon of it, and the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice offered to its well-willers; It inflamed my ſpirit with indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſet my very ſoule as it were all on fire; Inſomuch, that I went immediatly to old Mr. <hi>Colet,</hi> the Record-keeper of the Tower, and asked him, if hee had the originall Records of the Charters of <hi>London;</hi> and underſtanding he had them; out of my penury, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed three or foure pound for the Copies of thoſe that were moſt uſefull for me; and alſo the Copy of <hi>H.</hi> 5. prerogative, and unbind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proclamation: by vertue and authority of which, they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the rights of all the free men of <hi>London,</hi> in divers particulars, and as much as in them lies, annihilated divers of the antient and juſt Charters, and legall priviledges of this City confirmed by <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> and making further inquiry of a man verſed in antiquity, <hi>I underſtood that there was an antient book in print, above</hi> 100. <hi>yeares agoe, containing many of the Liberties and Franchiſes of London;</hi> for which I ſent into <hi>Duck-lane,</hi> and with ſome induſtry found it out,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:130934:12"/>
which is a moſt excellent book, which with the Records I ſent to a true friend of mine, to get him to tranſlate the Records into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and all the Latine and French that is in that book, who ſent unto me the fore-going Diſcourſe; which in regard he was a ſtranger to <hi>London,</hi> he was unwilling to ſet his name to it, and I reading the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and liking it very well, judged my ſelf bound in duty to my ſelf, and all my fellow-Commoners, <hi>the Cloak-men of London,</hi> to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it in print; and in regard, by Gods aſſiſtance, I intend ſhortly to publiſh and print the Records, with a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentary in point of Law upon them; I judged it convenient hereby, by way of Poſt-ſcript, to give you the underſtanding thereof; and alſo, to give you the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which moved me to reſolve, to hazard no ſmall adventure there upon, which are theſe:</p>
                        <p>Firſt, becauſe <hi>the Prerogative-Pattentee monopolizing Merchant ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers,</hi> have contrary to Right, Law, and Juſtice, robbed me of my trade, whoſe illegall, arbytrary, deſtructive practiſes, to the liberties, freedome, and proſperity of <hi>England;</hi> I have in my anſwer to Mr. <hi>VVill. Pryn</hi> (called <hi>Innocencie and Truth juſtified</hi>) punctually anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized, as there you may reade from page 48. to page 63. Now, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. <hi>If any provide not for his own family, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for thoſe of his own houſe, he hath denied the Faith, and is worſe then an Infidell;</hi> In which, to me is implyed, that a man muſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be provident and induſtrious to keepe and preſerve what hee hath, but alſo to maintain and defend his rights liberties, and proprieties, that they be not invaded or taken from him: and this made honeſt <hi>Naboth,</hi> that he would not part-with his Vineyard, his inheritance to wicked King <hi>Ahab,</hi> although he offered him very good tearmes for it, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.1, 2, 3. much leſſe ſhould I part with my trade, to any illegall Monopoliſer and every individuall Free-mans of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. and that not only by the principles of nature and reaſon, but alſo by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> as is not onely proved by the fore-named Diſcourſe, but alſo by another excellent Treatiſe, called, <hi>Diſcourſe for free Trade,</hi> publiſhed about two years agoe by a Merchant of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Secondly, the readineſſe of the <hi>Prerogative-Magiſtrates of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> to execute any illegall Commands upon the free-men thereof, and particularly upon my ſelf; as for inſtance, when I was priſoner in Newgate, illegally committed by the houſe of Lords, that had no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:130934:12"/>
juriſdiction over me in that caſe, and when upon the 22. of <hi>June</hi> laſt, by their Warrant, <hi>they commanded me to dance attendance at their Bar, for what cauſe they did not expreſſe:</hi> neither know I any Law extant that authorizeth them ſo to do. Which action, I looked upon, as a trampling the Lawes of the Land, and the Liberties of all the free Commons of <hi>England,</hi> under their feet; and therefore, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of further miſchiefe, I writ this following Letter to Mr. <hi>VVoollaſton,</hi> the chiefe Jaylor of Newgate under the Sheriffes of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <opener>
                                 <salute>SJR,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>I This morning have ſeen a Warrant from the houſe of Lords, made yeſterday, to command you to bring me this day at ten a clock be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, the Warrant expreſſeth no cauſe wherfore I ſhould dance attendance before them; neither do I know any ground or reaſon wherefore I ſhould, nor any Law that compels, mee thereunto; for their Lordſhips ſitting by vertue of Prerogative-pattents, and not by election or common conſent of the people, hath, as <hi>Magna Charta</hi> (and other good Lawes of the Land) tels me, nothing to do to try me, or any Commoner whatſoever in any criminall caſe, either for life, limb, liberty, or eſtate: but, contrary hereunto, as incrochers and uſurpers upon my freedomes and liberties; they lately and illegally endeavoured to try me a Commoner at their Bar, for which I under my hand and ſeale, proteſted to their faces againſt them, as violent and illegal incrochers upon the rights and liberties of me, and all the Commons of <hi>England</hi> (a copy of which &amp;c. I in Print herewith, &amp; ſend you) and at their Bar I openly appealed to my competent, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, legall tryers, and Judges, the Commons of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in Parliament (for which their Lordſhips did illegally, arbytrarily, and tyrannically, commit me to priſon into your cuſtody) unto whom divers dayes agoe I ſent my appeale &amp;c. which now remains in the hands of their Speaker, if it be not already read in their houſe, unto which I do, and will ſtand, and obey their commands.</p>
                              <p>
                                 <pb n="24" facs="tcp:130934:13"/>Sir, I am a free-man of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore I am not to bee uſed as a ſlave or Vaſſall by the Lords, which they have already done, and would further doe. I alſo am a man of peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>, and deſire not to moleſt any, if I be not forced thereunto: therefore I deſire you as you tender my good and your own; take this for an anſwer, that I cannot without turning traytor to my liberties; dance attendance to their Lordſhips Barre: being bound in conſcience, duty, to God, my ſelf, mine, and my Country; to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their incroachments to the death: which by the ſtrength of God I am reſolved to doe.</p>
                              <p>Sir, you may, or cauſe to be exerciſed upon me, ſome force or violence to pull and drag me out of my chamber, which I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to maintain, as long as I can, before I will be compelled to go before them; and therefore I deſire you, in a friendly way, to be wiſe and conſiderate before you do that, which it may be, you can never undoe,</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <salute>Sir,</salute>
                                 <signed>
                                    <hi>I am your true and faire conditioned priſoner, if you will be ſo to me,</hi> JOHN LILBURN.</signed>
                                 <dateline>
                                    <hi>From my Cock-loſt in the Preſſe-yard of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> 
                                    <date>
                                       <hi>this</hi> 13. <hi>of June</hi> 1646.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </closer>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </div>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>The Copy of the Order.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Lunae 22 Junij 1646.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ORdered by the Lords in Parliament aſſembled, that Lieutenant Colonel <hi>John Lilburn</hi> now a priſoner in Newgate, ſhall bee brought before their Lordſhips [in the High Court of <hi>Parliament</hi>] to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morrow morning by ten of the clock: And this to be a ſufficient War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in that behalf.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>To the Gent. Uſher of this Houſe, or his Deputy, to be delivered to the Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Newgate, or his Deputy.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Iohn Brown Cler. <hi>Parliamentorum.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:130934:13"/>Which Letter I ſent by my wife, and a friend; but they not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Mr. <hi>Wollaſton</hi> within, I ordered them to carry it to Mr. <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drick,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Foot, the Sheriffes of London his Maſters,</hi> whom they found at <hi>Guild Hall,</hi> at the <hi>Court of Aldermen;</hi> to whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered the letter, with my Proteſt againſt the Lords, and appeale to to the Houſe of Commons therein mentioned; who (as they told me) carried it in to the Court of Aldermen: and, as they judged, there read them. But, in ſtead of any remedy, according to my juſt expectation; I had my chamber wall immediatly after broke down by force, by <hi>Ralph Briſco,</hi> the Clerk of <hi>Newgate,</hi> and their Officer: &amp; a violent and forcible entry made into my chamber, and my perſon by force carried away before the Lords, who had no Legall, or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall power over me. I confeſſe, I was ſuddenly ſurprized, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt ten a clock at night before I knew of it: and ſo could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther provide my ſelfe of victuals, or any defenſive Armes; the which if I had had, I would (to the death) have defended my ſelfe againſt all the Officers in <hi>London</hi> that had come to have fetched me out of my Chamber (my legall Caſtle) by vertue of that illegall Warrant, to carry me before the Lords, who had nothing to doe with me: eſpecially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering I had legally proteſted againſt them; and legally appealed to the Houſe of Commons, my proper and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Judges; who had accepted, read, and approved of my appeale, as juſt and legall: And therefore not onely that buſineſſe, or procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Lords; but all their after proceedings: yea, the ſentence it ſelfe, in this very particular alone; was, and is, illegall: For they ought not, neither (in law) had they any ground to meddle or make with me any further; unleſſe the Houſe of Commons had judged my proceedings with the Lords, illegall, and had given mee up to them as my legall Judges to try me. And therefore the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front of the Lords (in point of right and priviledge) is as great to the Houſe of Commons, in proceeding to judgement againſt mee without their leave, or ſo much as ever deſiring it; as their uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are deſtructive to me and my Liberties, and the Liberties of all the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons of <hi>England:</hi> And opportunity they could not have had to have made me ſo fully as they did, the object or ſubject of their uſurpation; if it had not been that the prerogative-Sheriffs of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> had been as full of prerogative-Principles, as the Lords them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and as deſirous to deſtroy the Lawes and Liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:130934:14"/>
as they; for which I will never forgive them, till they have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged their great wickedneſſe therein, and made me (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law and Juſtice) ample reparations: which by Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance I will with all the ſtrength and might I have, unceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeek for.</p>
            <p>But their malice and indignation to mee, for ſtanding for the Lawes, Liberties, and Freedomes of <hi>England,</hi> ceaſed not here; but when the Lords committed me, by their tyrannicall order, cloſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner to <hi>Newgate,</hi> to be lockt up cloſe in my Chamber; Theſe Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary &amp; tyrannicall Sheriffes and their Officers executed it upon me to ſome purpoſe for 3 weeks together. For; contrary to all law and juſtice, they kept my wife from me, &amp; would not ſo much as ſuffer her, or any of my friends, to ſet their feet over the threſhold of my chamber doore: nor ſuffer my wife, ſervant, or any of my friends, to deliver either meat, drink, money, or any other neceſſaries. And when I preſſed the Jaylors to permit my wife to come into the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon yard, that ſo I might (in their preſence) ſpeak with her out of my chamber window; they abſolutely refuſed it, and told mee, I little knew what a ſtrict charge was laid upon them to the contrary, by the great ones at <hi>Guild-Hall.</hi> And therefore my wife was forced to ſpeak with me out of the window of a neighbouring houſe, at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fourty yards diſtance: whoſe cruelty and malice was ſo enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that they often threatned to boord and naile up the poore mans windows: Yea, <hi>Briſco,</hi> the Clerk came up into my chamber, and commanded me to forbeare ſpeaking to my wife, (although it were at ſuch a diſtance) or elſe hee would boord up my win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and ſo deprive me not onely of ſeeing and ſpeaking to my wife; but alſo rob me of the greateſt part of that little aire that I had coming in at my Caſements. But I bid him doe his worſt: for I would pull them down as faſt as he naild them up; or elſe if I could not, I would ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re to them, though it burnt the Houſe down to the ground: And alſo I would ſpeake to my wife in ſpite of his teeth, and all his great Maſters; unleſſe they either ſewed up my lips, or cut out my tongue. And then in a rage hee told me, Hee would carry me into <hi>Newgate</hi> it ſelf, and lay mee in a cloſe place, where I ſhould ſpeak with none, nor ſee none, whereupon I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to ceaſe his threatning of me; for I ſcorned him, and bid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to the malice of him and all the Men and Devils in earth and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:130934:14"/>
hell; having my confidence fixed in and upon that God that I knew would preſerve and keep me, and who by his power was able to deſtroy him, and ten thouſand ſuch, in the twinkling of an eye; tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that to lock me up in ſuch a place, was the ready way ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to get me my liberty: For then all my friends and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance would conclude, that the Lords had ſet his Maſters and him on to murder me: (as the <hi>Earle of Northampton,</hi> and the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> ſet <hi>Sir Gervis Elvis,</hi> the Lieutenant of the Tower, and <hi>Weſton</hi> his ſervant, to murder Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury</hi> in his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Tower of <hi>London;</hi> for which act they were both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly and juſtly hanged) which might hazard, at the leaſt, either the pulling down, or breaking open the priſon; to ſee what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of me: Therefore I wiſhed him to be adviſed what he did; for I aſſured him, I would improve all the intereſt I had in the world to effect it. For, before I will be murdered, I would ſell my life at as deare a rate as it was poſſible for me to ſell it at. And at another time I turned him to the Parliaments Declaration, 2 <hi>N.</hi> 1642. <hi>Book Declar. pag.</hi> 722.723. Where, ſpeaking of the difference betwixt the King and themſelves, in anſwer to ſomething ſaid by him about the interpretation of the Statute of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that they would take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his power from him; they demand a queſtion, How that doth appeare? And they anſwer, <q>Becauſe we ſay it is treaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> as well as the King of <hi>England;</hi> and becauſe we ſay, that the King of <hi>England</hi> hath not a power to deſtroy the lawes and people of <hi>England.</hi> And what is that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of that Statute, that no learned Lawyer will ſet his hand to? That treaſon may be committed againſt the <hi>Kings Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> though not directed againſt his <hi>Perſon.</hi> Doe there want (ſay they) preſidents, or Book-caſes to make this good? Or, is it not, that they cannot ſee wood for trees, that look after preſidents to prove this, which at length is acknowledged in his Majeſties Proclamation of the 18. of <hi>June?</hi> Is it then that interpretation of the Statute, that the raiſing of force in the maintenance of his Majeſties Authority, and of the Lawes, againſt thoſe that would deſtroy both it and them, is no treaſon, though ſuch acts of trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and rebels ſhould be in purſuance of his <hi>Majeſties perſonall commands,</hi> and accompanied with his <hi>Preſence?</hi> And have we cited no preſidents to this purpoſe? What are thoſe then of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:130934:15"/>
Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke, Robert de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eere,</hi> Duke of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the reſt in the time of <hi>Richard the ſecond,</hi> which we cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be publiſhed: whoſe levying of Forces againſt the authoriy of the Parliament, and to put to death divers principall members of both Houſes, by the <hi>Kings expreſſe command,</hi> which he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to accompany with his preſence; was by two Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>judged Treaſon:</hi> And the Act of ſuch levied forces to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them, was judged <hi>good ſervice</hi> to the Common-wealth. Theſe preſidents are ſaid to be grounded upon repealed Statutes: and wee have indeed heard it ſaid ſo twice; but wee never heard the Statute that repealed them, cited once. And whether the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of the <hi>eleventh of Richard the ſecond,</hi> was a more forced Parliament then that of the <hi>twenty firſt of Richard the ſecond,</hi> which repealed the Acts thereof: And whether that of the <hi>firſt of Henry the fourth,</hi> which repealed that of the <hi>twenty firſt of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard the ſecond,</hi> and all the acts thereof, and revived that of the <hi>eleventh of Richard the ſecond,</hi> and all acts made therein; was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet repealed: And conſequently, whether thoſe two acts of the <hi>eleventh of Richard the ſecond,</hi> and the firſt of <hi>Hen: the fourth,</hi> doe not ſtill ſtand in force; None that are acquainted with the Records and Hiſtory of that time, can deny, or ſo much as doubt. But doe we need Preſidents in this caſe? Is it not a known Rule in Law, <hi>That the Kings illegall commands, though accompanied with his preſence, doe not excuſe thoſe that obey him?</hi> And how then (ſay they) ſhall it excuſe Rebels and Traytors? and how ſhall it hinder the Kings Courts and Miniſters to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt them judicially, if they ſubmit; or by force, if they make oppoſition with force? If the King might controll all the Courts in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> and the High Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelfe, and make it good by force; what were become of the known legall government of this Kingdome? or what a <hi>Jewell</hi> had we of the Law? or what benefit of being <hi>Governed according to Law;</hi> if all Lawes might by force be overthrown, and by force might not be upheld and maintained?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now Mr. <hi>Briſco,</hi> ſaid I, if the Kings commands and power can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not overthrow the Law; much leſſe can the Lords commands, who are farre inferiour in power unto him, their abſolute earthly Creator and Maſter, from whom they have derived all that they have; and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:130934:15"/>
therefore cannot be above him. For it is a maxime in Nature and Reaſon, <hi>That there is no Being beyond the power of Being.</hi> And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maxime it is, <hi>That every like begets its like;</hi> but not more: And therefore impoſſible it is, that their power ſhould be above the power of their begetter, or Improver, the King.</p>
            <p>Again, Mr. <hi>Briſco,</hi> ſaid I, if here, by the confeſſion of the Lords themſelves; <hi>(for they joyned in the making of this very Declaration)</hi> it be a known Rule in Law, <hi>That the Kings illegall commands, though accompanied with his preſence, doe not excuſe thoſe that obey him;</hi> then much leſſe are you, your Maſter <hi>Wollaſton,</hi> nor his Maſters, the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes of London,</hi> excuſable, for executing the Lords illegall and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Warrants and Orders upon me; which they doe not accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with their preſence to ſee put in execution. Therefore, Mr. <hi>Briſco,</hi> aſſure your ſelfe, that if I live, I will turn all the ſtones in <hi>England</hi> that poſſibly I can turne, but I will have juſtice, ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and reparations from you and all your maſters, for executing the Lords illegall Orders and Commands upon me. At which hee told me, he and his Maſters were Officers, and muſt execute the commands the Lords gave them, without the diſputing the illegality of them. Wel then, ſaid I, by the ſame Rule, if the Lords (who have no legall authority over me) ſend you a Warrant to hang, ſtrangle, or ſtab me, or cut off my head in priſon, although I have had no le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall triall <hi>according to the Law of the Land;</hi> you will put it in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And as well, ſaid I, may you doe that, as to doe to me as you have done: and beſides I know no Ground they had to receive mee a priſoner upon the Lords Warrant, at all: eſpecially conſidering according to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the <hi>Petition of Right</hi> &amp;c. none of their Warrants of commitments of me, have either legall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or legall concluſions. And excellent to this purpoſe are thoſe <hi>Golden expreſſions</hi> of the moſt worthy Lawyer, Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in his expoſition of the 29. <hi>chap. of Magna Charta, in his</hi> 2. <hi>Part. Inſtit. fol.</hi> 52. Where expounding what is meant by <hi>per legem ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae,</hi> that is, the law of the land, having ſpoken of divers things, he comes to ſpeak of Commitments, and ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now ſeeing no man can be taken, arreſted, attached, or impriſoned, but by due proceſſe of law, and according to the law of the land; theſe concluſions hereupon doe follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, that a Commitment by lawfull warrant, either in deed, or in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:130934:16"/>
law; is accounted in law due proceſſe or proceeding of law, and by the law of the land, as well as by proceſſe by force of the Kings Writ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, That he or they which doe commit them; have lawfull authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, That his warrant or MITTIM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S be lawfull, and that muſt be in writing under his hand and ſeale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, The CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE muſt bee contained in the WAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANT, as for Treaſon, Felony, &amp;c. or for ſuſpition of Treaſon, or Felony, &amp;c. Otherwiſe if the MITTIM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S contain no cauſe at all, if the priſoner eſcape; it is no offence at all: Whereas if the MIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S contained the cauſe; the eſcape were Treaſon or Felony: though he were not guilty of the offence. And therefore for the Kings benefit, and that the priſoner may bee the more ſafely kept; the MIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S ought to contain the cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly, the Warrant, or MITTIM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S containing a lawfull CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE, ought to have a lawfull CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION, Viz. and him ſafely to keep, untill he be delivered by Law &amp;c. and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the party commiting doth further order. And this doth evidently appeare by the Writs of</hi> Habeas Corpus, <hi>both in the Kings Bench, and Common Pleas, Exchequer, and Chancery, which there Hecites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Mr. <hi>Briſcoe,</hi> I am <hi>a legall man of England,</hi> who in all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have declared a conformity to the lawes thereof, and have as freely adventured my life for the preſervation of them, as any Lord in the Land, whatſoever he be, hath done. And beſides, I have to doe with thoſe very LORDS that have ſtiled themſelves, <hi>The Conſervators of the Lawes and Liberties of England;</hi> and wiſh in their printed <hi>Declarations,</hi> the <hi>plague and vengeance of heaven to fall upon them, when they indeavour the deſtruction and ſubverſion thereof.</hi> And therefore I expect in every particular to be dealt with accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law <hi>(my inheritance, and the inheritance of all the free Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners of England)</hi> and not otherwiſe; and my life and blood I will venture againſt that man, what-ever he bee, that ſhall attempt the contrary upon me: for the Free-born men of <hi>England (yea the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of them) can neither by the command of the King, nor by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, nor Councell, nor the Lord of a Villain can, or could im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon, arreſt, or attach any man, without due proceſſe of law, or by legall judgement of his equalls, viz. MEN OF HIS OWN CONDITION, or the Law of the Land, againſt the forme of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:130934:16"/>
our defenſive great Charter of Liberty.</hi> Nay, in old time a Pagan or an Heathen could not be unjuſtly impriſoned, or attached, or arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, without due proceſſe of Law, as appeares <hi>by the Lawes of King Alfred, Chap.</hi> 31. and conſonant to this doctrine, and that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned in the Parliaments Declaration; is the judgment of Sir <hi>Edward Cook in the</hi> 186, 187. pages of the 2. part of his <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> and which was ſo reſolved for Law, as hee there declares 16. <hi>H.</hi> 6. and yet notwithſtanding all the diſcourſe I had with <hi>Briſcoe,</hi> the Sheriffes Clerk of Newgate, about 9 a clock at night; the Sheriffes the next morning ſent 30. or 40. of their Varlets that wait upon the Theeves and Rogues, and the Hang-man to Tyburn, to carry me by force, <hi>nolens, volens,</hi> to the Lords Bar <hi>(thoſe Vſurpers and Incrochers)</hi> to receive my moſt <hi>illegall, unjuſt, barbarous, and tyrannicall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My third reaſon is, becauſe I have not only been ſo evilly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly dealt with this year by the <hi>Sheriffes of London;</hi> but alſo the laſt year by the <hi>Lord Major of London, Alderman Atkins, and Mr. Glyn Recorder thereof,</hi> when I was committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> by the <hi>Houſe of Commons;</hi> for what, to this day, I doe not yet know: yet Mr. <hi>Glyn</hi> ſo thirſted after my blood, that as I was from very good hands credibly informed, he was a main ſtickler to get an Order to paſſe that Houſe, <hi>to have me tryed at the Seſſions of Newgate for my life;</hi> ſaying (as I am told) in the houſe, to ſome members thereof, <hi>turn him over to me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I will hamper him to the purpoſe:</hi> of which, when I heard; it was not for me to ſit ſtill; and therefore, I got pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed certain Quere's to ſtate my caſe, in one ſide of a ſheet or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: the ſubſtance of which, you may read in a printed Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Englands Birth-right.</hi> And what was the iſſue of that buſineſſe, you may fully and truly read in my fore-mentioned anſwer to Mr. <hi>Pryns</hi> notorious lyes, falſhoods, and calumnies; eſpecially, in pag. 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33 34. to which, I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>And then ſecondly, there was a falſe, and baſe report raiſed, ſpread, and divulged by Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi> and ſome other of my bitter Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Adverſaries <hi>(thoſe bloudy cozen-Germans to the perſecuting Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops)</hi> meerly to make me and my friends odious to the people that ſo inſtead of enjoying a legall tryall, and the benefit of the Law, <hi>our common Inheritance;</hi> we might by the rude multitude, be either ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death, or pulled in pieces: which report was, <hi>that I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:130934:17"/>
with other Separates &amp; Anabaptiſts to root out the Members of this Parliament by degrees, beginning with Mr.</hi> Speaker; <hi>whom if we could cut off, (as</hi> Pryn <hi>ſaith it in print,</hi> in his book, called, <hi>The Lyar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded) all the reſt would follow: and if this ſucceeded not, then, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe &amp; cut off this Parliament by force of Arms, &amp; ſet up a new Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of our own choice &amp; faction;</hi> my anſwer to which abominable falſe charge, you may read in my fore-mentioned anſwer to him, pa. 35. And there running divers of his Authentical witneſſes and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (little better then Knights of the Poſt) up and down <hi>London;</hi> and at laſt, one or more of them came into <hi>Houndsditch,</hi> to one Mr. <hi>Rogers, &amp;c.</hi> to inſnare him, and told him of the plot; but he like a wiſe man, apprehended him by a Conſtable, and carryed him before the then Lord Major, who dealt neither faire, honeſtly, nor juſtly with me, nor them; no, nor with the Kingdome, &amp;c. But in regard it may at a diſtance, touch upon ſome preſent Member or Members of the Houſe of Commons, with whom, I do ingeniouſly confeſſe, I have no deſire at all to conteſt; I ceaſe it: though it was as miſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous a plot againſt me, as ever in my life was contrived againſt mee, and which had come out to the bottome, if my Lord Major had been as juſt and honeſt, as a righteous Judge ought to be, and had not been ſo full of <hi>prerogative-principles,</hi> as to feare Man, more then God.</p>
            <p>My fourth reaſon, is, becauſe <hi>I have not only been robbed of my trade, by the monopolizing Merchant-Adventurers; and ſo evilly, hardly, and unjuſtly dealt with, by the late Lord Major, the two Sheriffes, and tho Jaylors of Newgate, all Mr. Recorders pride and malice, all prerogative Officers in London;</hi> but alſo, have been ſo evilly, illegally, and unjuſtly dealt with all, by Col. <hi>Francis West,</hi> the preſent Lieutenant of the Tower (thereunto appointed by the principall prerogative-men of <hi>London,</hi>) which you may briefly reade in a late publiſhed book of a friend of mine, called, <hi>Liberty vindicated againſt Slavery,</hi> and which I ſhall, by the help of God, fully lay open in due time; and alſo, in regard of that late abuſe, given unto my wife at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> at the very Parliament door, when ſhe was peaceably wayting there with eight Gentlewomen more of her friends, for an Anſwer to her late Petition, and for Juſtice from the houſe, about my illegall ſufferings, which it is their duty to hold put to her, and all others whatſoever, that have juſt cauſe to ſeek it from them; where came unto her
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:130934:17"/>
one <hi>Richard Vaughan,</hi> Enſign to the Guard that day, and a Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> being a Goldſmith in <hi>Foster-lane;</hi> who, after he had ſet his Guard at the doore, that goes into the Roome next to the Houſe of Commons: my wife, with other of her friends, ſtanding in a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able manner at the bottome of thoſe ſtaires; hee came, and enquired of them which was <hi>Lilburns wife;</hi> at which my wife anſwered, <hi>ſhe was ſhe;</hi> upon which he wiſhed, I had been out of the Land when I firſt went out in the Parliaments ſervice; and without any more adoe, laid violent hands upon her, and endeavoured to throw her down the next ſtaires, which are three or four ſteps, that goe down into the Court of Requeſts, and had gone neer to have ſpoyled and undone her, if ſome of her friends by her, had not preſerved her from the fal: but being not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent with this, he followed her into the Court of Requeſts-chamber, and then again laid violent hands upon her, and took her by the throat, as if he would have throtled her, and would have drag'd her away as a priſoner, calling out to his armed men to help him: a piece of unmanlike cruelty and barbariſm, which will be in future ages, a badge of ſhame to the ſufferers of it, to go unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and which renders him to be one of the malicious, baſeſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthieſt, and cowardlieſt of men, to uſe a Gentlewoman in ſuch a barbarous manner, that neither affronted, nor medled, nor made with him, and which makes me judge him to be a fellow more fitter to feed hogs and Swine, then to be named a Soldier, or ranked amongſt the number of martiall men: but yet notwithſtanding, it gives me cauſe to think, and judge, that ſome of my prerogative-adverſaries either in the City, or elſe-where, ſet him on of purpoſe, at laſt, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and affront my wife; that ſo, ſhe ſhould never dare any more to come thither to ſeek for juſtice, at the hands of thoſe who have ſworn to hand it over impartially to every legall man &amp; woman of <hi>England.</hi> The comparing of which, with what I have but very late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heard, puts my thoughts into a deep and ſerious muſe: the late relation of which, as it is told me, is thus; That day my wife deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered her Petition in print to the Members of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>there was a Barriſter at Law in the Lords Houſe</hi> (it ſeemes before they ſate) <hi>reading my wifes Petition, and there came a Lord to him, and ſaid unto him in a familiar manner, What art thou reading?</hi> unto which; he anſwered, <hi>the Petition of Lieut. Col.</hi> Lilburns <hi>wife to the Houſe of Commons:</hi> Unto which that Lord ſaid, <hi>the Plague on
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:130934:18"/>
him for a Rogue; how are wee troubled with him? but if the</hi> Lords <hi>would be ruled by me, and be all of my mind; we would diſpatch him, and ſtretch him up without any more adoe:</hi> But truly, my Lord, I muſt tell you, you have no Law to do it, I am ſure of it; and therefore in reference to that, <hi>I challenge you, and your whole Houſe, to a tryall of Law, for all the differences betwixt us,</hi> begin when you pleaſe: and your Lordſhip knowes very well, that when I was laſt at your Bar, <hi>I challenged you all face to face to a tryall at Law:</hi> But, my Lord, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I find and meet with ſuch ready Inſtruments, amongſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative-men of <hi>London,</hi> my unnaturall fellow-Citizens, to put in execution, without diſpute, feare, or check of Conſcience; (all your unjuſt Commands) I have ſome cauſe to be jealous, that I may meet with Sir <hi>Thomas Overburies</hi> portion, to be murdered in priſon, there being a very near parallell betwixt divers of his uſages and mine, as appears to me, by the printed relation thereof, made by the Right Honourable <hi>Foulke,</hi> Lord <hi>Brooke,</hi> and printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>N. R.</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>And therefore, for all theſe reaſons laid together, I am reſolved, both in point of conſcience, prudence, and ſafety, to ſit no longer in ſilence; but to give to you Lords, and your Kinſmen, <hi>the prerogative men of London</hi> (by ſome of whom, I have ſuffered ſo much of late, &amp; have juſt cauſe to fear, that they will be your arbitrary and illegall Inſtruments, to make me yet ſuffer much more) a joynt and home-charge both together; and this I ſend you forth, as a forlorn Hope: the body of which (do all of you the worſt you can) by the ſtrength of God, ſhall follow after; although you ſhould tye, and fetter both my hands and feet, and ſet twenty Warders upon me, to keepe mee from Pen and Ink: for I am now reſolved, by the power of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, to ſell my life to you my conjoyned adverſaries and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as dear (if it be poſſible) as ever <hi>Sampſon</hi> did his to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines:</hi> of whom it is ſaid, he did them more miſchiefe at his death, then he did them in all his life, <hi>Judg.</hi> 16. and good reaſon have I ſo to do, in point of conſcience; both in the ſight of God, and all rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall men that are not diſtempered with the principles of pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall cowardlineſſe; and that I prove thus:</p>
            <p>If to do <hi>to another, as we would have another to doe to us,</hi> be a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, ſo acceptable to God, and all good men, and an unalterable Law eſtabliſhed by God, before <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, and under his Law, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:130934:18"/>
alſo eſtabliſhed by Chriſt, the juſt and righteous Prince of peace, under the Goſpel; as the moſt tranſcendent excellenteſt Law, that can be amongſt the ſons of men, and which purely flowes, from the pure fountaine of reaſon: then from the ſame pure principle of reaſon and Juſtice; I deduct this which naturally ariſeth from the leſſe to the greater;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which in point of conſcience is unlawfull for me to do to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is much more in point of conſcience, unlawfull to do unto my ſelfe:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, to do evill unto another, to miſchiefe, rob, ſpoyle, kill, or any way deſtroy another, in point of conſcience, is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full;</p>
            <p>And therefore, in point of conſcience, it is much more unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me to do any evill unto my ſelfe, or to miſchiefe, rob, ſpoyle, kill, or any way deſtroy my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon of all is, <hi>becauſe in my ſelf, is nature nearer to my ſelf then all the world beſides.</hi> And again, if by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand of God, and the inſtinct of nature; I muſt as much as much as in me lyes, do good to all men: then by the ſame ſtrength of reaſon, <hi>muſt I much more do good unto my ſelfe.</hi> And therefore for me to know of, and ſee miſchiefe before my eyes intended me, and to be ſo ſtupid and ſottiſh, as not to take care, by all juſt and rationall meanes to prevent it; is to be fellonious to my ſelfe, and to do that unto my ſelfe, which I ſhould not do unto another, no, nor ſuffer to be done unto another: But my adverſaries have taken from me, <hi>my liberty, (and tormented and tortured my body with cruel and cloſe impriſonment) and ſpoyled me of my trade and liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and disfranchiſed me without cauſe or ground, by robbing me of my right and benefit in the lawes and liberties of England (more deare to me then any earthly treaſure whatſoever) and thereby as much as in them lyes, have made a ſlave and a beaſt of me, and ſo changed the property that God created me in: and now thirſt after my life and blood, which is all they have left me.</hi> To preſerve which (finding no remedy at the hands of Juſtice (by the powerfull operation of ſome prerogative-men there, the names and qualities of whom you ſhall ſhortly knowe) to whom I have appealed; I ſend my adverſaries this bone to pick, as aſpeciall meanes (appearing ſo to my underſtanding) to breake their cruel fangs, and devoure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:130934:19"/>
tusks; and <hi>the mighty and omnipotent power of the Lord JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH, goe along with it, and make it effectuall for the accompliſhing that end.</hi> And I hope no rationall man will blame me for doing herof, ſeeing as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>eye for eye, tooth for tooth, and all that a man hath will he give,</hi> (or venture) <hi>for his life.</hi> And ſo much for the particular reaſons concerning my ſelfe, which moved me to write this.</p>
            <p>I will onely give you two more, which are more generall; and then conclude.</p>
            <p>And the firſt is, <hi>becauſe the greateſt bondage of this land ariſeth from the monopolizing patentee-Clergy,</hi> who have been and ſtill are the men that as <hi>Iohn</hi> in his <hi>Reu.</hi> (Chap. 7.1.) ſaith, hould the four winds of the earth, that the winde thereof ſhould not blow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth. And though in <hi>Pauls</hi> time, <hi>ſome preached the Goſpel of envy, and others of good will;</hi> yet he forbids none to preach it; <hi>but rejoyceth that it was preached by any, whether in pretence or truth,</hi> yea, <hi>and thereat would rejoyce,</hi> Phil. 1.15.16.17.18 But theſe Clergy-men, like ſo many of the Divels Agents, whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is a Kingdome of darkneſſe; ſet themſelves on purpoſe to overſpread the earth, with blindneſſe and darkneſſe, and ſo by conſequence; with injuſtice, cruelty, and blood-ſhed: and rather then any, though never ſo able, ſhould preach Chriſt and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, that will not receive power; therefore, from them, by their mouldy, greazy conſecration and impoſition of hands; <hi>thouſands, and ten thouſands of ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> ſhall periſh for want of knowledge, and ſo run headlong to hell eternally: yea, men that will not be conformable unto them, and be abſolutely of their cut, and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; though never ſo extraordinarily adorned with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, and of his will and minde; <hi>ſhall neither eat, and drinke, buy, nor ſell amongſt them, no nor live, nor have a habitation</hi> amongſt them in the land of their nativity: witneſſe that moſt DIVELISH, WICKED, BLOODY, VNCHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN, PAPISTICALL REMONSTRANCE <hi>of the prerogative-men of London,</hi> &amp;c. who amongſt many other baſe and wicked deſires, would have us reduced back to the Pope of Rome againe, <hi>to believe as the Church believes;</hi> for they <hi>would have us be conformable in Church Government,</hi> &amp;c. not onely to what is already eſtabliſhed, <hi>but what ever ſhall be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed:</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:130934:19"/>
and to ſpeake properly, this very Remonſtrance is but one of their brats, which with other of their actions, doth demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate them cleerly to be part of that Antichriſtian beaſtly power, ſpoken of <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. And what Doctor <hi>Leighton</hi> in his booke called <hi>Syons Plea,</hi> pag. 69. ſaith of the prelates in reference to the popiſh Biſhop; may we ſay of the preſent Clergy in reference to the Biſhops, whoſe office and function they have condemned for Antichriſtian, viz. <hi>that they are garments cut out of the very ſame cloth, a paire of ſheeres</hi> (as we ſay) <hi>went but betweene them, only divers hands have cut them out.</hi> And to me it is the greateſt riddle in the world, how the Biſhops can be Antichriſtian as themſelves ſay, and themſelves Chriſts Miniſters, although they have no other ordination but what is derived from them, ſeeing as nature tells me, <hi>every like begets its like:</hi> and reaſon alſo tells me; <hi>that there is no being, beyond the power of being:</hi> and the Scripture ſaith, without all contradiction, the leſſe is bleſſed of the greater, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.7. but no where ſaith, the better or greater is bleſſed of the leſſer: and <hi>Iames</hi> demands a queſtion which in reaſon, and the ordinary courſe of nature is impoſſible to be, ſaying, <hi>Iames</hi> 3.11. <hi>doth a fountaine ſend forth at the ſame place, ſweet water and bitter?</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> demands to know who he is, <hi>that can bring a cleane thing out of an uncleane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe Clergy-men demonſtrating by all their actions, that they are the naturall and true-bred children of their bloody fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Prelates, if not worſe then they; for all their faire ſpeeches and gloſing pretences to the contrary: therefore we may ſafely avert, that propoſition to be true of them, that Doctor <hi>Leighton</hi> in the foreſaid booke, pag. 51. averrs and proves to be true of their ſpirituall forefathers, viz. that of all the evills in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and of all the good hindered, ſince Anno. 600; one or more of the hierarchy, have been a principall cauſe. And I add and averr, that there is no miſery befallen this Kingdome, nor no good hindered from coming to it, ſince the Prelates were put downe; but ſome of the preſent Clergy have been the maine principall in it, witneſſe their continuall and daily dividing and diſtracting the Kingdome in all the parts of it, on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et purpoſe for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing that diviliſh and tyrannicall intereſt of pride, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:130934:20"/>
and Domination, which they will effect, or elſe they will lay it in blood and force. Witneſſe their bloody intended Ordinance, brought in by Mr. <hi>Tate,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bacon.</hi> And have they not alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy almoſt brought us to the doore of a new warre with the <hi>Scots;</hi> which, God prevent. But, if for a plague to us it ſhould come upon us; I hope the people of <hi>England</hi> will have their eyes opened to ſee the Clergy to be no ſmall cauſes of it, whom I hope they will not let paſſe without due puniſhment, as grand diſturbers of the peace of this diſtreſſed Common-wealth: Seeing that the temporall and trade-Monopolizers, and other prerogative-men in <hi>London,</hi> are their ſtalking-horſes, by which they act their deſignes the more ſtrongly: the one helping the other to inſlave the people, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are and may juſtly be called <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> brethren in evill, and wickedneſſe, whoſe tyrannicall myſtery wants an Anatomy, the beginning of which; this is.</p>
            <p>The laſt reaſon why I publiſh this, is, becauſe that although the fundamentall Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> be rationall and juſt lawes, and ſo pleaſant and delightſome to the people: theſe Prerogative-Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polizing Patentee-men of <hi>London,</hi> have done as much as in them lies, to pervert them, and to turn them into Wormwood and Gall: And though they be the common birth-right and inheritance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular individuall freeman of <hi>England;</hi> yea, of the meaneſt Cobler and Tinker, as well as of the greateſt Gentleman or Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. And therefore juſtly doth the King call the Law, <hi>The Birth-right of every ſubject of this Kingdome. Book Declar.</hi> 312. and in pag. 328. he ſaith, <hi>The Law is the common inheritance of his people.</hi> And in pag. 385. he calls the Law, <hi>The common Birth-right of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;</hi> to which onely, they owe all they have beſides: And therfore are bound in the <hi>defence of it,</hi> to bee made <hi>MARTYRS</hi> for it. And in pag. 28. he ſath, <hi>The Law is not onely the inheritance of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubject, but alſo the onely ſecurity he hath for his life, liberty, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: And the which, being neglected, or diſeſteemed;</hi> (under what ſpecious ſhewes ſoever) a great meaſure of infelicity, if not an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable confuſion, muſt without doubt fall up them. The meaneſt of which, he ſaith, p. 650. <hi>are born equally free,</hi> (and to whom the Law of the Land is an EQUALL INHERITANCE) <hi>with the greateſt Subject. And that the wealth and ſtrength of this Kingdome, is in the number and happineſſe of the people; which is made up of men
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:130934:20"/>
of all conditions: and to whom in duty without Diſtinction, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth</hi> he oweth <hi>an EQVALL Protection.</hi> And he in pag. 140. 163. paſſeth a moſt ſuperlative high commendation upon thoſe golden expreſſions of Mr. <hi>John Pyms</hi> ſpeech againſt the Earle of <hi>Strafford:</hi> and publiſhed in print by a ſpeciall order of the Houſe of Commons, which are, <hi>That the Law is the SAFEGVARD, the CVSTODY of all private intereſts: Your honours, your lives, your liberties, and eſtates; are all in the keeping of the Law: And without this, every man hath alike right to any thing. And therefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Law is that which puts a difference betwixt good and evill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt juſt and unjuſt. If you take away the Law, all things will fall into a confuſion; every man will become a law unto himſelf: which, in the depraved condition of humane nature, muſt needs produce many great enormities: Luſt will become a law, and envy will become a law, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and ambition will become lawes: and what dictates, what divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſuch lawes will produce; may eaſily be diſcerned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this very language doth the Parliament ſpeak in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, <hi>Book Declar.</hi> pag. 6. where they ſpeak with a great deal of vehemency and bitterneſſe againſt the bold and preſumptuous injuſtice of ſuch Miniſters of Juſtice as before this Parliament, <hi>made nothing to breake the lawes, and ſuppreſſe the liberties of the Kingdom, after they by the Petition of Right, &amp;c. had been ſo ſolemnly &amp; evidently declared.</hi> Yet <hi>they obſtructed</hi> (amongſt abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of other grievous crimes there enumerated, <hi>the ordinary courſe of Juſtice;</hi> which they there (pag. 7.) call the <hi>COMMON BIRTH-RIGHT</hi> of the Subjects of <hi>England.</hi> And in pag. 38. they ſpeaking of the Kings dealing with the five accuſed Members: who, by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Warrant, had their <hi>Chambers, Studies, and Trunkes ſealed up: Which action</hi> (they ſay) <hi>is not only against the priviledge of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the common liberty of every Subject.</hi> And in the ſame page they ſay, <hi>His Majeſty did iſſue forth ſeverall warrants to divers Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers under his own hand, for the apprehenſion of the perſons of the ſaid members, which by Law he cannot do; there being not all this time, any legall charge, or accuſation, or due PROCESSE of law iſſued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, nor any pretence of charge made known to that Houſe whereof they were Members. All which are against the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall lawes and liberties of the Subject, &amp;c.</hi> And in pag. 458, 459. they declare, <hi>That in all their endeavours ſince this Parliament began, they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:130934:21"/>
have laboured the regaining of the ancient</hi> (though of late yeares much invaded) <hi>rights, lawes, and liberties of England, being the Birth-right of the Subjects thereof.</hi> And therefore pag. 660. they own it as their duty, to uſe their beſt endeavours, <hi>That the meaneſt of the Commonalty may enjoy their own Birth-rights, freedome, and liberty of the law of the land; being equally</hi> (as they affirm) <hi>intitled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto with the greateſt Subject.</hi> And in pag. 845. they declare, that to be aſſaulted or ſeiſed on without due Proceſſe or Warrant; <hi>is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the legall priviledge of every private man:</hi> but the Prerogative-Monopolizing arbitrary-men of <hi>London,</hi> as though they had an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Deity-power in themſelves, and were to be ruled and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by nothing, but the law of their own will: And as though they were more abſolute and ſoveraigne in power, then either the King or Parliament, divided or conjoyned; diſ-franchiſing the greateſt part of the Commons of <hi>London,</hi> of their Liberties, Trade, and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, at their pleaſure; which is granted unto them not onely by God, and the great Charter of Nature, and Principles of Reaſon, but alſo by the <hi>Fundamentall Lawes and Conſtitutions of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> by which lawes, and by no other; is <hi>London,</hi> as well as the reſt of <hi>England,</hi> to be governed. And therefore Arbitrary, Irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and Illegall it is for them, or any of their brother-hoods, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolizing Corporations and Companies, by the authoirty of any pretended Royall Patent, Proclamation, or Commiſſion, whatſoever; to aſſume unto themſelves a power to deſtroy, annihilate, and make voyd the Fundamentall lawes of the Land; which yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they daily doe. And ſure I am, by the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> the King of himſelf can neither make an oath, nor impoſe 6 pence upon any of his people, nor impriſon, nor puniſh any of them, but by the Law, &amp; by the Statutes of <hi>Magna Charta, chap.</hi> 29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>E.</hi> 2.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>E.</hi> 3.8.9. <hi>The King ſhall neither by the great Seal, nor little Seale, diſturb, delay, nor deferre judgment, or common right: And though ſuch commandements doe come; the Juſtices ſhall not therefore leave to do right in any point.</hi> But yet notwithſtanding, they meerly by their illegall prerogative, both frame oathes abſolutely-deſtructive to the publick law of the kingdome: impoſe arbitrary fines, and illegall levies and payments of moneys: and act illegall impriſonments and puniſhments: yea, and at their pleaſure ſeiſe upon the goods of free-men. All which is conſtantly practiſed in their Patentee-Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:130934:21"/>
               <hi>Companies, Corporations</hi> and <hi>Fraternities.</hi> So that to ſpeak properly, really, and truly, their <hi>Brotherhoods are ſo many conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to deſtroy and overthrow the lawes and liberties of England, and to ingroſſe, inhance, and deſtroy the trades and Franchiſes of moſt of the Freemen of London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if it ſhould be objected. That theſe things are the ancient cuſtomes and practices of the Grandees of <hi>London:</hi> and therefore by preſcription of time are become lawes thereto;</p>
            <p>I anſwer: Courſe of time amends not that which was nought from the beginning. And that which was not grounded upon good right, and found reaſon; is not made good by continuance of time. And therefore to give a definition of the Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> as it may be proved out of the workes of the beſt and moſt conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lawyers thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It conſiſts of the ancient conſtitutions, and modern acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, made by the States of the Kingdome: but of theſe onely ſuch as are agreeable to the word of God, and law of Nature, and ſound Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or the Fundamentall Law of the Land, is the PERFECTION <hi>of Reaſon, conſiſting of Lawfull and Reaſonable Cuſtomes, received and approved of by the people: and of the old Conſtitutions, and modern Acts of Parliament, made by the Eſtates of the Kingdome. But ſuch only as are agreeable to the law Eternall and Naturall,</hi> and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God: For whatſoever lawes, uſages, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, not thus qualified; <hi>are not the law of the land:</hi> nor are to be obſerved and obeyed by the people, being contrary to their Birth-rights and Freedomes, which by the Law of God, and the <hi>great Charter of Priviledges,</hi> they ought not to be.</p>
            <p>And therefore Sir <hi>Richard Empſon,</hi> and <hi>Edm. Dudley,</hi> Juſtices of Peace, were both hanged in <hi>Henry</hi> the eighths dayes, for putting in execution, ſeverall illegall practices grounded upon an unjuſt law made in the 11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.1. which, as honorable Sir <hi>Edw. Cook</hi> ſaith, <hi>was made againſt, and in the face of the Fundamentall Law of the great Charter,</hi> 2. <hi>part. Inſtit. fol.</hi> 51.</p>
            <p>And juſt it was they ſhould be thus dealt with, becauſe it is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, beneficial and profitable for the Common-wealth, that guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſons ſhould be puniſhed, leſt by the omiſſion of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one, many men by that ill example, may be encouraged to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:130934:22"/>
commit more heinous offences. And excellent to this purpoſe, is that ſaying of the Parliament, which I deſire they may never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, <hi>Book, Declar</hi> pag. 39. which is, <hi>That they are very ſenſible, that it equally imports them, as well to ſee juſtice done against them that are criminous, as to defend the juſt rights and liberties of the Subjects and Parliament of England.</hi> And therefore pag 656. they call the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the law, <hi>the very life and ſoule of the law,</hi> as indeed it is: without which; it is but in truth a dead letter, and a ſenceleſſe block. But woe unto you prerogative Patentee-Citizens, if the Law ſhall be executed upon you; I profeſſe I will not give three pence for an hundred of your eſtates, for all the greatneſſe rhereof, what-ever become of ſome of your liberties, or lives; which many of you have hitherto preſerved by bribes, and other indirect courſes. Witneſſe ſome of you in a jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt fraternity, like brethren in evill, giving above <hi>threeſcore thouſand pounds</hi> at once for a bribe in the dayes of the Councell-Table, to preſerve you from Law and Juſtice; and to deſtroy the Law, and to buy and rob your fellow-Citizens, as free as your ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves, of their liberties, franchiſes, trades, and livelihoods. Read the Diſcourſe for <hi>Free Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onlye worſe then <hi>high-way men, pick-pockets, &amp; houſebreakers,</hi> who now would fain transform your ſelves into Angels of light, like your old wicked Father, &amp; become godly Presbyters, that now-ſprung-up Sect and Hereſie in <hi>England;</hi> whoſe Lordlineſſe and pride, was long ſince as Heatheniſh, and Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iliſme, condemned by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and zealous Covenanters, which you make your ſtalking horſe, to disfranchize all honeſt and tender conſcience men, that cannot take that impoſſible to be kept, and double-faced Covenant, the greateſt make-bate and ſnare, that ever the Divell, and the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy his Agents, caſt in amongſt honeſt men in <hi>England,</hi> in our age; which I dare pawn my head and life ſo to prove it to be, in a fair &amp; publike diſcourſe, againſt the greateſt maintainer thereof in <hi>England.</hi> But alas! If it were ten times worſe, your weſons are wide enough to ſwallow it down, and your conſciences large enough to diſgeſt it, without the leaſt danger of vomiting: But I hope the true, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and juſt God of Heaven and Earth, will raiſe up heroical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to unvaile, and unmask you, and bring about wayes &amp; means enough, for all your jugling, and machivel-like endeavours, to divide the peoples affections, each from other, about thoſe unhappy names
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:130934:22"/>
of <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> to bring you to condigne, and juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved puniſhments, before you have fully ſadled and bridled them, and made them fit to be rid by you as ſlaves: And therefore, for the further diſcovery of you, I judge it not amiſſe, here to inſert, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Petition of Mr. <hi>William Sykes,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Johnſon,</hi> delivered in writing firſt to the houſe of Commons, and then in print to the Members thereof; which thus followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Honourable the <hi>Knights, Citizens,</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> of the <hi>Commons Houſe</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> Aſſembled.</head>
                        <head>The humble Petition of <hi>William Syeks,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Iohnſon,</hi> Marchants, on the behalfe of themſelves, and all the freemen of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THat whereas divers Marchants in the 21. year of the Raign of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> obtained a large and illegall Charter of incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, for them and their Company, to uſe the traffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que and ſeat of Marchandize, out, and from any of Her then Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions, through the <hi>Sound</hi> into divers Realmes, Kingdoms, Dominions, Dukedoms, Countries, Cities, and Townes, <hi>viz. Norway, Swethi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, Poland,</hi> &amp;c. Whereby none but themſelves, and ſuch as they ſhall think fit, and for ſuch fines and compoſitions as they ſhall impoſe, ſhall take any benefit by the ſaid Charter; disfranchiſing thereby, all other the free-borne people of <hi>England,</hi> who during the time of all theſe warres, have been in divers reſpects, greatly charged for the defence of this preſent Parliament; the lawes and liberties of their native
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:130934:23"/>
Country, and therefore ought indifferently to enjoy the benefit of the good lawes, franchiſes, and immunities by <hi>Magna Charta</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed: which great Charter hath been ratified by 31. ſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Parliament; as alſo this preſent Parliament, being bound by proteſtations, oaths, and covenants to maintaine the ſame: by reaſon whereof, and other illegall monopolies, they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from that free inlargement of common traffique, which the Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> do enjoy; the ſame being deſtructory to their laudable liberties and priviledges, the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall lawes of the Land, to the manifeſt impoveriſhing of all owners of ſhips, maſters, mariners, clothiers, tuckers, ſpinſters, and multitudes of poore people; beſides the decreaſe of cuſtoms, the ruine and decay of navigation, together with the abating the price of our wools, cloth, ſtuffe, and ſuch like commodities, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and growing within this Ralm, and the inhauncing of all commodities imported from thoſe forraign parts, by reaſon of the inſufficiency of the merchants, they being few in number, and not of ability to keepe the great ſtore of our ſhips and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men a work, and to vend our native manufactories, and likewiſe by reaſon that thoſe forraign commodities are in few mens hands, much hurt and prejudice hath redounded to every private or freeman of this Kingdom, and tendeth to the ruine of the conſtitutions thereof.</p>
                        <p>Your Petitioners moſt humble ſuit is, that the charter and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoly of the <hi>Eaſtland</hi>-merchants, the charters and monopolies of the merchant <hi>Adventurers, Turkie</hi>-marchants, <hi>Greenland</hi>-marchants, <hi>Muſcovia</hi>-merchants, &amp;c. upon miſ-informations, and untrue pretences of publike good, ſo unduely obtained, and unlawfully put in execution, to the great grievance and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of the free Denizons of this Realm, contrary to the great Charter, and divers other ſtatutes of former Parliaments, <hi>viz.</hi> the 12. <hi>H.</hi> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the 3. <hi>Jac.</hi> which was made for the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Corporation, &amp;c. the Petition of Right, the act made for the aboliſhing of the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament (in which our liberties and freedoms are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed) may be, as indeed they are, declared to be contrary to law, and to be utterly void, and of none effect, and in no wiſe to be hereafter put in execution: and this we are the rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:130934:23"/>
to crave, for that the Parliament in the 3. <hi>Car.</hi> by the Petition of Right, and this Parliament by the act for aboliſhing the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> have confirmed the ſtatute of tallage, made in the 34. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. whereby in the 4. chaptar, it is enacted; that we ſhall have our lawes, liberties, and free cuſtoms, as large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wholly as we or our anceſters have uſed to have the ſame at any time, when we had them at the beſt: and if any ſtatute hath been made, or any cuſtome brought in contrary to them; that ſuch manner of ſtatutes and cuſtoms, to be void and fruſtrate forevermore: and by another ſtatute of the 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. yet in force, and unrepealed, It is enacted, that if any Iudgement be given contrary and againſt the ſubjects liberties, confirmed by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> by any Iuſtices, or by any other Miniſters, that hold plea before them; the ſame ſhall be undone, and holden for nothing: all which your Petitioners doubts not but you will grant and confirme, and no more ſubject your Petitioners to thoſe law-deſtroying monopolizers: but that free trade and traffique may be reſtored in all points, according to law, as of right it ought to be: theſe Corporations called to a ſtrict account for all their wrongs and oppreſſions, and reparations made to the parties grieved, as ſhall be agreeable to juſtice (the life and ſoule of all well-governed Common wealths) that all men hereafter to ſucceeding generations, may be terrified from making in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chroachments upon the common liberties and freedoms of the people.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And your Petitioners ſhall ever pray,</hi> &amp;c.
<list>
                                 <item>William Sykes.</item>
                                 <item>Thomas Johnſon.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>March the</hi> 4. 1645.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And I doe hereby exhort all my fellow-Citizens that have been denied and prohibited by you to follow their trades and vend their goods, ſeriouſly to read over the Statute of Monopolies, made 21. <hi>James,</hi> chap. 3. and ſeriouſly with the beſt advice and counſell they can get, conſider thereof; and I believe they will, by it, finde your practiſes to be againſt the Fundamentall Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and your ſelves liable to pay treble dammages, and double coſts, to every man that ſhall ground his action upon this Statute; and, <hi>ſue you at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-law, for hindering, grieving, diſturbing, or diſquieting, or his, or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:130934:24"/>
their goods, or chattels, any way ſeizing, attaching, diſtraining, taking, carrying away, or detaining by occaſion, or pretext of any Monopoly, or of any ſuch Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion (as in the Declaratory-part of this Statute, is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) grant, licence, power, liberty, faculty, Letters-Pattents, proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, inhibition, reſtraint, warrant of aſſiſtance, or other matter, or any thing tending as aforeſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the incouragement of all thoſe, that ſue upon this moſt excellent Law; it is enacted in the body thereof, <hi>That he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes an action grounded upon this Statute, incurs a Praemunire, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Statute of the</hi> 16. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>But if you ſhall think, that you are free, by reaſon of the 5. <hi>proviſo</hi> therein contained: I believe you are meerly cuzoned; for if you read the Preamble or Declaratory-part of the Statute, you ſhall find it there declared, <hi>That all grants of Monopolies, and of the benefit of any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Lawes, or of power to diſpence with the Law, or to compound for the forfeiture, are contrary to Law;</hi> So that thereby it appears, the antient fundamentall known law of the Land, is abſolutely againſt Monopoliſts; ſo that this Statute is no new law, but a declaration and confirmation of the old and juſt law of the Land, which makes the Statute the more ſtronger: but leaſt it ſhould in future time, by any ſcrupulous or cautious Judge, be queſtioned, whether it bee a true Declaration of the Law: Therefore, to make it ſtrong, without ſtaggering; it is not only declared to be law, but it is <hi>enacted to be ſo,</hi> and that by all the eſtates, in a free and peaceable time; which makes it as firme, and ſure, without the leaſt flaw in the world, as it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any humane law to be made: And therefore, for the avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and preventing of the like miſchiefs in future time, as had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the Kingdome in times paſt, to the great grievance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of the people; May it pleaſe your moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, at the humble ſuit of the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, <hi>That it may be declared and enacted; And be it declared and enacted, by authority of this preſent Parliament, That all Monopolies, and all Commiſſions, Grants, Licences, Charters, and Letters Pattents, heretofore made or granted, or hereafter to be made or granted to any perſon or perſons, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies politike, or corporate whatſoever, of, or for the ſole buying, ſelling, making, working, or uſing of any thing within this Realme or the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Wales, or of any other Monopolies, or of power, liberty, or facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:130934:24"/>
to diſpence with any others, or to give licence or toleration to doe, uſe, or exerciſe any thing againſt the tenour or purport of any Law or Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, or to give or make any Warrant for any ſuch diſpenſation, licence, or toleration to be had or made or to agree, or compound with any others for any penalty, or forfeitures limitted by any Statute, or of any Grant or promiſe of the benefit, profit, or commodity of any forfeiture, penalty, or ſumme of money, that is, or ſhall be due by any Statu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, before judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereupon had, and all Proclamations, Inhibitions, Reſtraints, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants of Aſſiſtants, and all other matters and things whatſoever, any way tending to the inſtituting, erecting, ſtrengthening, furthering, or countenancing of the ſame, or any of them; are altogether contrary to the Lawes of this Realm, and ſo are, and ſhall be utterly void, &amp; of none effect, and in no wiſe to be put in ure or execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I pray tell me, ye Monopolizers of <hi>London,</hi> of what ſtrength, validity, or authority, is your proviſo againſt this ſtrong declared Law? truly, not worth a button, being abſolutely weaker, then all the other 9 Proviſoes.</p>
            <p>But let us a little conſider of your proviſo; the concluſion of which, expreſly ſaith, <hi>That your Fraternitie, Charters, Cuſtomes, Corporations, Companies, Fellowſhips, and Societies, and their Liberties Priviledges, Powers, and Immunities, ſhall be, and continue of ſuch force and effect</hi> (mark it well) <hi>as they were before the making of this Act, and of none other: any thing before in this Act contained,</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teary, <hi>in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi> And truly, they were all of them illegall before, and therefore of no force and effect, as is fully proved and declared in the Preamble, ſo that you get not the breadth of a hair, either in point of benefit or power, by this proviſo. But, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, your Pattents, Charters, &amp;c. are not onely <hi>declared</hi> and <hi>enacted,</hi> to be illegall, but alſo your eſtates liable to pay treble dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and double coſts, to all men that you wrong, contrary to this juſt and excellent Law: in which, beſides the incurring the Premu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire, to any that ſhall delay an Action grounded upon this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute: It is alſo enacted, <hi>That no Eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ign, Protection, Wager of Law, Aid Prayer, Priviledge, Injunction, or order of reſtraint, ſhall in any wiſe be prayed, granted, admitted, or allowed, nor any more then one imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the further illuſtration, that the Proviſo of <hi>London</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, both the <hi>declaratory,</hi> and <hi>penall part,</hi> of this Statute; ſeriouſly read
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:130934:25"/>
and conſider, the ſtrength of the five laſt proviſoes, which onely are fenced in unqueſtionably, and you ſhall find their proviſoes run clear in another ſtrain to that of <hi>London,</hi> viz. <hi>Provided alſo, and be it enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that this Act, or any Declaration, proviſion, diſablement, penalty, or other thing before in the Act mentioned; ſhall not extend to, &amp;c.</hi> and in the concluſion of their proviſo, the words run thus. <hi>That all &amp;c. ſhall be, and remain of the like force and effect, and no other, and as free from the declarations, proviſions, penalties, and forfeitures contained in this Act, as if this ACT had never been had nor made, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But compare the proviſo for <hi>London</hi> (which is abſolutely the weakeſt of the reſt) and you ſhall find no ſuch words in it at all; the words of which Proviſo; thus followe:</p>
            <p>"Provided alſo, and it is hereby further intended, declared, and enacted; that this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not in any wiſe extend, or be prejudiciall unto the City of <hi>London,</hi> or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny City, Borough, or Towns-Corporate within this Realm; for, or concerning any Grant, Charters, or Letters-Pattents to them, or any of them, made or granted, or for, or concerning any cuſtome or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes uſed by or within them, or any of them, or unto any Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, or Fellowſhips of any Art, Trade, Occupation, or Myſtery, or to any Companies, or Societies of Merchants within this Realm, erected for the maintenance, enlargement, or ordering of any Trade of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize; but that the ſame Charters, Cuſtomes, Corporations, Companies, Fellowſhips and Societies, and their liberties, priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, powers, and immunities ſhall be and continue of ſuch force and effect, as they were before the making of this Act (which was juſt none at all) and of no other: any thing before in this Act contained to the contrary in any wiſe: notwithſtanding, the Statute of 3. <hi>James, chap.</hi> 6. which Statute opens and make free, the trade for <hi>Spain, Portugall,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> with Sir <hi>Edward Cookes</hi> Coment upon the Statute of Monopolies, in the 3. part of his <hi>Inſtitut. fol.</hi> 181. and his ſayings upon the ſame ſubject, in his Expoſition of <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> 2. part, Inſtitut. fol. 47. is extraordinary well worth the judicious Readers ſerious peruſall; for they will give a great deale of light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe Monopoliſts, &amp;c. But in caſe the Reader have not the bookes by him, nor cannot furniſh himſelf therewith without a great deal of money; if he pleaſe to furniſh himſelf with my fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:130934:25"/>
Treatiſe (which for a very ſmall matter he may) called <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie and Truth juſtified,</hi> and read the 55, 56, 60, 61, 62. pages there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: you ſhall finde there, both the fore-mentioned Statute at large, and the marrow of Sir <hi>Edward Cookes</hi> Aaguments; to which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you.</p>
            <p>But if any man ſhall propound the queſtion, and ask what's the reaſon that the Statute of Monopolies, being a Law of ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, to all the people of <hi>London,</hi> is no plainer penned.</p>
            <p>I anſwer (according to that information that I have from every good hand, and one that knowes as much of the hammering contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and paſſing of that Statute; as I think any one man in <hi>England</hi> doth) that in the Parliament before this moſt excellent Law paſſed, it was in more plainer expreſſions then now it is ſent up to the Lords, who judged it ſo prejudiciall to the Prerogative, and divers great Courtyers, that with ſcorne and indignation they tare it in their houſe, and threw it over their Bar; ſo that there was an end of it for that Parliament: But it being of ſo much uſe to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as it was; ſome Patrons thereof in the next Parliament, ſet it on foot again, and proſecuted it very cloſe: but judging it impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, purely without clogs to paſſe the Lords; and if it did paſſe the Lords, yet they feared it would ſtick at the King; and therefore put in ſome colourable proviſoes, which not one in a hundred could rightly underſtand: but it coming into the Lords houſe with the proviſoes, much all alike, the ſubtle, crafty, Attorney Generall, then Sir <hi>Thomas Coventry</hi> late Lord-Keeper preſently found out the falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; and being put upon it by his Maſter the King, ſtrengthened the five laſt proviſoes as they are, which principally ſerved his turn, and beating then a good-wil to the Common-wealth and the Law of the Kingdome, paſſed by that proviſo of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. that ſo the Act might be as beneficiall for the Kingdom, as poſſible it could bee got to be then: and to be the promoters of that Statute, were willing to pleaſe the King and his Courtiers, in admitting the five laſt provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoes, having gained <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. being the main and principal of all the reſt, rather then not to have it paſſe at all; which then it was impoſſible to do without them: and therefore there was an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary great neceſſity, to pen it ſo ambiguous &amp; doubtful as it is, not only for caſting a miſt over the Citizens eyes, as indeed they have done it excellently well; who if it had been plain, perſpicuous, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:130934:26"/>
eaſie to their underſtandings, would have interpoſed with all their might and ſtrength: and if they could not have prevailed to ſtop it in the Houſe of Commons; would have gone near to have bribed all the Courtiers about the Court (in which practiſes they are very well verſed) before it ſhould have paſſed either with the Lords, or King.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the Patentee-Monopolizers are ſo pernicious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the lawes and liberties of <hi>England,</hi> as by conſtant expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience they are found to be; that both informer Parliaments, and this preſent Parliament, the Houſe of Commons have thrown di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Patentee-Monopoliſts, out of the Houſe; as altogether unfit to be law-makers, who have been ſuch law-deſtroyers. It had been pure Juſtice indeed, if they had made no exceptions of perſons; but ſwept the Houſe of all ſuch: and then the King in his Declaration of the 12. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1642. <hi>Book Declar.</hi> pag. 516. had not had ſo much cauſe too juſtly to hit them in the teeth, with being partiall in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, Juſtice <hi>Laurence Whittaker, &amp;c.</hi> who the King there ſaith, <hi>hath been as much imployed as a Commiſſioner in matters of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as any man.</hi> And by all the information that I can get, or heare of, from thoſe that knew him well before the Parliament; the King in this particular hath ſpoken nothing but truth: and I am ſure, and will to his face make it good, <hi>ſecundum legem terrae</hi> (that is by the law of the land, but not by the arbitrary law of Committees, that his eſtate and head will not make a ſufficient ſatisfaction to the kingdome for thoſe intolerable In-rodes that he hath made ſince this Parliament, into &amp; upon, the fundamental and eſſential liberties, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges, and lawes of <hi>England.</hi> Therefore to you my fellow-Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, the Cloke-men of <hi>London,</hi> I make this exhortation, to make a petition to the Parliament, to bring him, &amp; all ſuch Delinquents, to condigne puniſhments: which both the moſt of you, and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t are bound unto (not only by your own intereſt, but alſo) by your proteſtation, &amp;c. <hi>Book. Declar.</hi> 156. 191. 278, 629. And good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement you have from their own Declarations, ſo to doe: For there they ſay, <hi>Book. Decl.</hi> 656. <hi>The execution of Juſtice is the very ſoul and life of the law.</hi> And pag. 39 they ſay, <hi>They are very ſenſible, that it equally imports them, as well to ſee juſtice done againſt them that are criminous, as to defend the juſt rights and liberties of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Parliament of England.</hi> And in pag. 497. they ſay, <hi>Woe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:130934:26"/>
them if they doe not their duty.</hi> Therefore never think that the Parliament will be worſe then their words, or throw their own Declarations behind their backs: and therefore if you want the fruit of them; blame your ſelves for not preſſing them to make them good unto you. For I am ſure it is their own Maxime and ſaying, that, of the Parliament there ought not to be thought or imagined a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable thing, page 28. and therefore, as they would have men to believe the truth of this Maxime; ſo undoubtedly they will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry careful and wary not to do a diſhonourable action, much leſſe to protect viſible Delinquents and Offendors amongſt themſelvs in the great Councel of the Kingdom, which were not only a diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble action, but would juſtly open all rationall mens mouths (not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to think, but alſo) to ſpeak diſhonourably of them.</p>
            <p>But it may be, you will ſay, that your Grandees of <hi>London</hi> tell you, the Parliament will receive no Petitions from a multitude of Citizens, unleſſe it come through the Common-councel.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, true it is, there hath been a very ſtrong report of ſuch a thing in <hi>London;</hi> but roguery, knavery, and ſlavery is in the bottome of it: for if the prerogative-men of <hi>London</hi> could once bring you to that; they might tyrannize over you at their pleaſure, ten times more then they do. Therefore, an enemy to the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>London</hi> in the higheſt degree; hee is that would perſwade you, to believe any ſuch thing: Yea, and I ſay further, he is an enemy to the honour, dignity, and ſafety of the Parliament that ſo doth: for this were to deſtroy the fundamentall freedomes of <hi>England,</hi> which the Parliament themſelves cannot deſtroy, being appointed to provide for our weal, but not for our woe, Book Decl. p. 150, 81, 179, 336, 361, 382, 509, 663 721, 726. and themſelves ſay, pag. 700. that all intereſts of truſts are for the uſe of others, for their good, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rherwiſe.</p>
            <p>And puniſhable is he, that ſhal make the people believe any ſuch thing: the Parliament judging it the greateſt ſcandal, that can be laid upon them, that they either do, or ever intended ſuch a thing, as to inſlave the people, and rob them of their liberties and freedomes, Book Decl. p. 264, 281, 494, 496, 497, 654, 694, 696, 705, 716.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when the King chargeth it upon them as a crime, that they have received Petitions againſt things that are eſtabliſhed by Law; they acknowledge it to be very true, <hi>And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:130934:27"/>
ſay, that all that know what belongeth the courſe and practice of Parliament, will ſay, that we ought ſo to do; and that both our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, and his Majeſties Anceſtors have conſtantly done it, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other place, wherein lawes, that by experience may be found grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and burthenſome, can be altered or repealed; and there being no other due and legall way, wherein they which are agrieved by them, can ſeek redreſſe, Book Decl. pag.</hi> 720.</p>
            <p>Yea, and when his Majeſty hits them in the teeth, with the great numbers of people that uſed to come up to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Parliament, calling them tumultuous numbers; <q>They tell him, that they do not conceive that numbers do make an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly unlawfull; but when either the end, or manner of their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage ſhall be unlawfull. Divers juſt occaſions (ſay they) might draw the Citizens to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where many publike and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Petitions, and other cauſes were depending in Parliament, and why that ſhould be found more faulty in the Citizens, then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of great numbers every day to the ordinary Courts of Juſtice, we know not, <hi>Book Decl. p.</hi> 201. 202. <hi>And therfore, pag.</hi> 209. they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that ſuch a concourſe of people, carrying themſelves quietly and peaceably (as they did) ought not in his Majeſties apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor cannot in the interpretation of the Law, be held tumultary and ſeditious:</q>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore up and be doing againe, as then you did, and alſo petition for the exemplary puniſhment of thoſe amongſt themſelves, that have robbed you of your <hi>Lawes, Liberties, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes,</hi> and <hi>Trades;</hi> for beſides all that is before named, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is behinde, namely, the <hi>disfranchiſing</hi> of all you <hi>Clokemen of London,</hi> in giving any vote in chuſing your Burgeſſes for Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, although I am confident you are above three hundred, for one <hi>Livery-man,</hi> and although your Perſons and Eſtates, I dare ſay it have been voluntarily ten times more ready and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable, in theſe late diſtractions, to preſerve the Parliament, and the Kingdome, and the lawes and liberties thereof, then the Gowne or Livery-men; although you be rob'd, by them of yours. Truly for my part, I ſpeake from my ſoule, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, without feare, I know no reaſon <hi>(unleſſe it can be proved that you are all ſlaves &amp; vaſſals(</hi> why you ſhould be concluded by the determinations, orders, and decrees of thoſe, that you
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:130934:27"/>
have no vote in chuſing: (for it is a true and juſt maxim in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>no man can binde me but by my own conſent</hi>) neither do I ſee how in reaſon or conſcience it can be expected from you, to pay any taxes, &amp;c. but that the whole charge that is layd upon this City, ſhould totally be borne by the Aldermen, and the Livery men till you be actually put in poſſeſſion, and injoy your equall ſhare in the lawes, liberties and freedoms thereof; as by the law of nature, reaſon, God and the land, yea, and your own an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and originall Charters, the meaneſt of you ought to do, as fully and largely in every perticuler, as the greateſt of them.</p>
            <p>And now I am upon this theame, I will make bold humbly to propound or declare to the conſideration of the Parliament, an inſufferable injury, and wrong, that is done unto thouſands of the freemen of England, by vertue of <hi>Prerogative Charters,</hi> and corporations, and the reſtrictive and unjuſt ſtatute of the 8. <hi>H.</hi> 6. chap. 7. Firſt, by <hi>Prerogative Charters,</hi> the King makes corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of what paltery Townes he pleaſeth, to chuſe two Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſes for the Parliament, in diver of which a man may buy a Burgesſhip for 40. or 50. l. and in ſome of which is ſcarce, 3. le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall men to be found according to the Statute of 8. <hi>H.</hi> 6 7. that is to ſay, <hi>men that are worth</hi> 40. s. <hi>in land by the yeare, above all charges,</hi> and in others of them, are ſcarſe any but Ale-houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, and ignorant ſots, who want principles to chuſe any man, but only thoſe, that either ſome lord, or great man writes for, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends; or elſe one who bribes them for their votes; and this undenezing of thoſe Corporations, is an undenezing to all the towns and villages adjacent; in which live thouſands of people, that by name are free-men of <hi>England,</hi> and divers of them men of great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates in money and ſtock; which alſo alſo are <hi>disfranchiſed,</hi> and <hi>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezed,</hi> by the fore-mentioned <hi>unrighteous Statute;</hi> becauſe they have not in land 40. <hi>s. per annum,</hi> and ſo ſhall have no vote at all in chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any Parliament man, and yet muſt be bound by their Lawes, which is meer <hi>vaſalage;</hi> and beſides, unrighteous it is, that <hi>Cornwall</hi> ſhould chuſe almoſt 50. Parliament-men; and <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> twice as big, and three times as populous, and rich, not half ſo many; and my poor Country the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham,</hi> none at all; and ſo indeed, and intruth, are meer vaſſals and ſlaves, being in a great meaſure like the <hi>French Peaſants,</hi> and the <hi>Vaſſals</hi> in <hi>Turkie:</hi> but the more fooles
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:130934:28"/>
they: for I profeſſe, for my part, I would loſe life and eſtate, lived I now in that Country, before I would pay 6. d. taxation; unleſſe it might enjoy the <hi>common, and undeniable priviledge in chuſing, (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and all the Countries in <hi>England,</hi> beſides, do) Knights and Burgeſſes, to ſit and vote in <hi>Parliament:</hi> the greateſt hinderer of which, at the preſent, I judge to be old Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aine</hi> and unworthy <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> thereof, who hath done more miſchiefe to that poor Country, by his <hi>negligence,</hi> if not abſolute <hi>wilfulneſſe, perfidiouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>treachery,</hi> (the diſcovery of which you may partly read in the 19, 20, 21. pages of <hi>Englands Birth-right;</hi> and which I underſtand is likely ſhortly more fully to be <hi>anatomized</hi> (if he turn not the more honeſter and juſter ſpeedily) by them or him, that to the death will avouch it,) then his life and eſtate can make ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And therefore, me thinks it were a great deale of more Juſtice and Equity, to fixe upon the certain number of the men, that the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> ſhould <hi>conſiſt of at</hi> 500. <hi>or</hi> 600. <hi>or more, or leſſe, as by common conſent ſhould be thought moſt fit;</hi> and equally to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion out to every County, to chuſe a proportionable number, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the rates, that each County by their Bookes of Rates are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, to pay towards the defraying of the Publique charge of the Kingdome; and then each County equally and proportionable by the common conſent of the People thereof to divide it ſelfe into <hi>Diviſions, Hundreds,</hi> or <hi>Wapentakes,</hi> and every Diviſion of and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves, <hi>to chuſe one or more Commiſſioners to ſit in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſutable to the proportion that comes to their ſhare: which would put an end and period to all thoſe inconveniencies that rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happen, which are mentioned in the foreſaid Statute of the 8. <hi>H.</hi> 6, 7. and reſtore every free-man of <hi>England,</hi> to his <hi>native,</hi> and <hi>legall rights and freedomes:</hi> Oh! that <hi>England</hi> might enjoy this peace of pure Juſtice; the which if it do not, the free-men thereof may blame themſelves.</p>
            <p>But now to return back to the City, and its prerogative-Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polizers, who, and their predeceſſors, I may juſtly ſay, have been main and principall Inſtruments of all <hi>Englands</hi> woe and miſerie; as I dare pawn my life upon it, cleerly, juſtly, and rationally to demonſtrate: for what hath brought all the preſent wars upon us, but the unjuſt ſwelling of the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> beyond the <hi>juſt Bounds</hi> of the known, and eſtabliſhed Law? and who hath put the <hi>arbitrary commands</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:130934:28"/>
in execution; but principally the <hi>Monopolizing Citizens?</hi> as in hundred of particulars, might cleerly be evidenced, and furniſhed the <hi>King</hi> from time to time, and year to year, with <hi>vast ſums of money,</hi> to ſupply his <hi>extravagancies,</hi> and the <hi>extravagancies of his extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Courtiers,</hi> which did inable him to break off <hi>former Parliaments at his pleaſure,</hi> and to keep them off, ſo long, till this poor Kingdome with oppreſſion and injuſtice was almoſt deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>And ſure I am, if the King had found none to obey, or put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution his illegall commands; our former miſeries, and theſe preſent warres had never been: and impoſſible it would have been for the King to have kept off Parliaments ſo long as he he did, if theſe men and their predeceſſors had not been beginning, originall, and ill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents, illegally (from time to time for their own particular ends and advantages) to ſupply his neceſſities with vaſt <hi>ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney:</hi> yea, I have heard it from very good hands, of ſolid and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Citizens, <hi>That after the breaking up of the Parliament in the third of this King, the Corporation of MERCHANT AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VENT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RERS, freely and voluntarily without any compulſion, made a moſt unjuſt, and England-deſtroying and inſlaving order, in their Company, TO PAY VNTO THE KING CV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STOMES, &amp;c. for all their Merchandiſe, contrary unto law, and the liberties of England.</hi> Yea, and in affront of the late, or moſt excellent Parliament that had made the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> by which all royall impoſitions, and levies whatſoever, are damn'd: and not onely enacted, but alſo declared, to be againſt the Fundamentall lawes of the kingdom; and yet I never heard of any of theſe men, whoſe life and eſtate was made a juſt ſacrifice there-for; although to my underſtanding, they as much, if not more, deſerve it, then the <hi>Earle of Strafford,</hi> But contrary to their deſerts, divers of the <hi>Grandees</hi> of this very <hi>Monopoly,</hi> and illegall <hi>Corporation,</hi> are become the great Treaſurers of the kingdomes money, both in the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome-houſe, and Exciſe; contrary to law, right, equity and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: which action of the Parliaments, in putting them into thoſe a grand places, loſeth the Parliament more in the affections of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of honeſt people; and will, if not ſpeedily prevented, make a greater breach in the peace of this diſtreſſed kingdome, then all their eſtates <hi>confiſcated</hi> will repay: For people doe already very much murmure, and begin privatly to queſtion the intentions of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:130934:29"/>
Parliament in reference to theſe men: and many begin to ſay, that this demonſtrates unto them, that they ſhall but only have a change of Maſters, and not of their <hi>Bondage, ſlavery,</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion;</hi> ſeeing ſuch <hi>Varlets, Vipers, Peſts, enemies and deſtroyers of the lawes and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of England</hi> imployed in the great <hi>Places</hi> of the kingdom, who muſt needs act according to their old and corrupt principles, and drive on their habituated and deſtructive deſignes againſt the weale, peace, trade, and tranquillity of this poore bleeding kingdome. And if (ſay the people) theſe worſt of men, who eat up mens trades and livelihoods, and ſo ſuck their bloods, as Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned diſcourſe well obſerves, and deſtroy men and this poore kingdome, with <hi>a ſecret deſtruction,</hi> ſhall poſſeſſe the Cuſtome-houſe; are they not enabled thereby to curb every Merchant that hath any Principles in him for the lawes and freedomes of <hi>England;</hi> are they not enabled hereby, to ſend their <hi>agents, creatures,</hi> and <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> to all the Ports and Sea-townes of <hi>England,</hi> where, they have an influence into the elections of all the Burgeſſes that in any of them are choſen to ſit in Parliament. By means of which we may have (ſay they) wickedneſſe, bondage, ſlavery, and all kind of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies eſtabliſhed by a Law: and then <hi>our laſt error will be worſe then the firſt,</hi> and all our money, &amp; blood, and fighting, ſhed and ſpent in vain. And have not the Exciſe-men the ſame power in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, in their hands likewiſe: For can they not, yea doe they not ſit upon the skirts of every man that hates and oppoſes their <hi>tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing</hi> and <hi>monopolizing</hi> wayes? And doe they not <hi>authorize,</hi> and ſend their <hi>Sub-commiſſioners, &amp;c.</hi> into all the Counties and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in <hi>England,</hi> where they have the ſame influence into all ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that their brethren at Cuſtome-houſe have in Sea-ports and Havens? Nay, theſe <hi>Blades</hi> ſtrengthen their intereſt, and make it double. <hi>Threfore look about you Gentlemen, before it be too late.</hi> For ſure I am, were it not for thoſe unhappy, unnaturall and irrationall diviſions, that theſe men (with the help of their Monopolizing bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Clergy) have made amongſt us; I am aſſuredly and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently perſwaded, that neither the <hi>King nor the Scots,</hi> nor yet the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Lords, would be ſo high in the <hi>Inſtep,</hi> as they are; which is like to beget a new warre again. For ſhame therefore unite in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, though you cannot in judgement, in matters of Religion, and ſtudy and ſtand for your <hi>common intereſt,</hi> lawes and liberties, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:130934:29"/>
take heed the <hi>French</hi> come not creeping in at a back doore: For they have already got <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and ſo are furniſhed with a good <hi>Harbor</hi> and ſtore of ſhipping, from whence with a faire wind they can in 6 or 8 hours land in the coaſts of <hi>Kens, Eſſex, Suffolk</hi> or <hi>Norfolk:</hi> Therefore beware of thoſe two dangerous places, <hi>Lin,</hi> &amp; the Iſle of <hi>Lovingland,</hi> hard by <hi>Yarmouth:</hi> therefore up, and as one man, to the Parliament with a Petition, to diſplace all thoſe <hi>Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and to put honeſt <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> into their places, that love the <hi>Fundamentall lawes,</hi> and the <hi>common</hi> and juſt liberties of the Nation; And alſo deſire the Parliament to reduce the publick treaſure of the kingdom, into the cheap, publick, and old good way of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The Exchequer for theſe obſcure clandeſtine wayes of theſe mens receiving and paying moneys, is not ſafe nor profitable for the kingdome, if you will beleeve Mr. <hi>John Pyms</hi> Speech, made at the Barre of the Houſe of Peeres againſt the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> which is a moſt excellent ſpeech. And alſo deſire the Parliament, not onely to remember, but alſo <hi>cordially, heartily,</hi> and <hi>really</hi> to put in execution their ſelfe-denying Ordinance, that they themſelves may be examples of ſelf-deniall to all the men in the kingdome. For a hard matter is it for any Parliament-man what-ever he be, in ſuch times of diſtreſſe as theſe are, wherein Souldiers that have ventured their lives for eight pence a day, to ſave both the Parliament and the kingdome, and many poore Widowes and fatherleſſe children, that have loſt their husbands and Fathers in the warres, and are now ready to ſterve and periſh for want of bread; and yet cannot get their ſmall arreares. And when the kingdome is reduced to that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, that Exciſe and Taxes muſt be laid upon poor men, that have wives, children and families, and nothing to maintain them with, but what they earn with the labour of their lands, and the ſweat of their browes, and yet then for &amp;c. to have great places of 1000. l. 1500. l. or 2000. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> and the ſalaries and ſtipends of them paid out of the publick ſtock, when they are able to live in pomp and gallantry of themſelves beſides: and it is poſſible to get honeſt, faithfull, and experienced men, that have ventured life and all for the common wealth, to officiat in thoſe places, as well, if not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for 100. l. or 150. l. or 200. l. <hi>per annum:</hi> let ſuch men, if there be any profeſſe what honeſty or Religion they wil;l I profeſſe ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that to me ſuch actions, at ſuch a time as this; are cleare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:130934:30"/>
to me, that ſuch men have neither honeſty, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, nor Religion; but meerly make them pretences for their own unworthy ends.</p>
            <p>And this Parliament being now a ſtanding Parliament, and like ſo to continue; it is very hard that the Lawyers thereof ſhould run from Bar to Bar to plead cauſes before Judges made by themſelves, who dare not eaſily diſpleaſe them, for feare of being turned out of their places by their meanes. Sure I am, well and conſcienciouſly to officiate the ſingle place of a Parliament man; is enough for one.</p>
            <p>But to return again to the Monopolizers, the endevourers, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of <hi>Englands</hi> deſtruction. If <hi>Alex.</hi> Archb. of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and <hi>Rob. de Veere,</hi> Duke of <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> deſerved to be proſecuted as traytors, for but endeavouring at the Kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand to deſtroy certain members of both Houſes: How much more doe theſe law-and-kingdome-deſtroying <hi>Monopolizers,</hi> deſerve the ſame, that have not onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured the deſtructions of ſome Parliament-men, but alſo the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Being of all <hi>Parliaments themſelves;</hi> and ſo by conſequence; the <hi>whole kingdome.</hi> Sure I am, if the Commonalty of <hi>London</hi> will carefully peruſe their own ancient and juſt <hi>Charters,</hi> they ſhall find, <hi>That they within themſelves have power enough not onely to diſfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe all theſe Monopolizers,</hi> but alſo <hi>all other freemen of London that ſhall endevour the deſtruction of their ancient fundamentall and juſt Freedomes, Liberties and Franchiſes:</hi> And that they, namely, the <hi>Commonalty,</hi> have not onely liberty <hi>to chuſe their Lord Maior,</hi> and that not onely from amongſt <hi>the Court of Aldermen;</hi> but alſo if they pleaſe, they may <hi>chuſe a diſcreet man from amongst themſelves: And the Commonalty in every Ward; upon a fixed day, are inabled once e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very yeare to chuſe an Alderman in every Ward, with an expreſſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, that one man ſhall not be Alderman two yeares together.</hi> And the Commonalty expreſly have a power to chuſe <hi>Chamberlaine,</hi> common <hi>Sergeant, Bridge-maſter,</hi> &amp;c. and to whom alone they are to be accountable for the moneys in their offices received.</p>
            <p>Now having brought this Diſcourſe to this period; it behoves me a little to Apologize for my ſelfe: becauſe I beleeve I ſhall have <hi>a whole ſea of indignation</hi> to ariſe againſt me; which I heere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I feare not, nor value, if I may have faire play, and have not my hands and feet bound, and then challeng to fight, and defend my ſelf. And truly I muſt ſay, and that in the preſence of God. I have
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:130934:30"/>
in the ſingleneſſe of my heart, <hi>without ends of my owne; diſcharged my conſcience: the boylings of which I could not withſtand,</hi> being at the writing hereof in <hi>Jeremies</hi> caſe, when he ſaid, pleading with God, <hi>Thy word was in my heart as a burning fire ſhut up in my Bones, and I was weary with forbearing, and I could not ſtay,</hi> Jer. 20.9.</p>
            <p>But yet, becauſe what-ever I meet with beſides, I <hi>perſwade my ſelfe</hi> I am ſure to meet with the revilings, and reproches of the barking curs of the times, ſuch as (S. <hi>Shipard</hi>) &amp;c. who in my cloſe captivity have nibbled at my heeles, like brats of the old Serpent; I ſhall therefore, for my preſent apologie, publiſh to the view of the world, the dealings of Mr. <hi>Iohn White,</hi> a Warder in the Tower with me, who lately writ a moſt falſe and ſcandalous book againſt me, &amp; with much importuning the Lieutenant of the Tower, (being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited Pen, Ink, and Paper) I obtained leave from him, upon certain conditions made with him, to write an anſwer to it; which was, that I ſhould not in the leaſt meddle with his maſters that committed me; and to let him ſee it, before it was printed, which I performed. But my Angatoniſt, old <hi>Iohn White,</hi> as it appears to me, hearing the Anſwer was very plain, and home Engliſh; ſent me a meſſage by a Gentleman, my fellow-priſoner, <hi>That he deſired to put the difference betwixt us to arbitration:</hi> And I being a man of peace, and willing to avoid jangling, if it were poſſible; upon agreement to compoſe it.</p>
            <p>I did chuſe two of my fellow priſoners, ſtrangers to me, and men of oppoſite principles; but knowing the Juſtice of my cauſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing convinced <hi>of the morall Juſtice of the Gentlemen:</hi> I choſe Sir <hi>Lewis Dive,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Morton;</hi> and he chuſe Sir <hi>John Strangewayes,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Glanvill;</hi> and the firſt day of the hearing of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was before Col. <hi>Francis West</hi> Lieutenant of the Tower at his own houſe, where we both referred our ſelves, to ſtand to the finall award of our foreſaid Arbitrators: at which hearing, they were pleaſed to give my <hi>Antagoniſt</hi> certain dayes time to procure Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, to prove the eſſentials of his Charge; and he out-ſtripping the time, and I lying under his publike diſgrace and calumny; I preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them for a concluſion: upon which they iſſued out this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Warrant.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="warrant">
                        <p>WE whoſe names are ſubſcribed, <hi>Arbitrators</hi> indifferently choſen to end all differences betwixt Lieutenant-Colonell <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi>
                           <pb n="61" facs="tcp:130934:31"/>
of the one party, and Mr. <hi>John White</hi> one of the Warders of the Tower of the other party, have appointed to morrow next at three of the clock in the afternoon, at Mr. Lieutenants houſe in the ſaid Tower, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to hear, and finally to determine the ſaid differences; whereof wee deſire the ſaid parties to take notice, and then to be preſent with their Witneſſes, and all ſuch proofe, as they will uſe in the premiſes. Given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our hands this <hi>5.</hi> of October, <hi>1646.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Glanvill.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Strangewayes.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Lewis Dive.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>William Morton.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But the next day, the Lieutenants office not permitting him to be preſent at the finall hearing; we all met at <hi>Sergeant Glanvils</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where after a large and faire hearing, they made this award un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their hands and ſeales; <hi>the Copy of which, thus followeth:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="award">
                        <p>
                           <q>TO all true Chriſtian people to whom theſe preſents indented ſhall come;</q> We Sir <hi>John Strangewayes,</hi> Sir <hi>Lewis Dive,</hi> Sir <hi>John Glanvill,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Morton</hi> Knights, Arbitrators, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore (that is to ſay, upon the 26. day of <hi>Septemb.</hi> laſt paſt, before the date hereof) indifferently choſen by Lieutenant Col. <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> "of the one party, and <hi>John White,</hi> one of the Warders of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> of the other party, for the ending of all differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and matters of controverſie betwixt them; having entred into the hearing of the ſaid differences, and matters of controverſie, upon the ſaid 26. day of <hi>September,</hi> and having upon the 6: day of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <q>moneth of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1646. in the 22. Yeare of the Raigne of our Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charles,</hi> fully heard the ſaid differences, and matters of controverſie; Doe find the ſame to be, and ariſe by, and upon the writing and publiſhing in print, of a certain Book, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>John Whites Defence,</hi> in behalf of himſelf, &amp;c. againſt a lying and ſcandalous Pamphlet, written by <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> entituled, <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vindicated againſt Slavery:</hi>
                           </q> In the 7. p. of which Book, to written, and publiſhed by the ſaid <hi>John White;</hi> he intimateth, That the ſaid <q>Lieut. Col. Lilburn, was, and is the Author of another ſcandalous Libell; entituled, <hi>An Alarum to the Houſe of Lords:</hi>
                           </q> and in a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:130934:31"/>
                           <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> added to the ſame Book of the ſaid <hi>John White,</hi> pag. the 12; he alleadgeth the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> to be the Author and "contriver of a printed Letter, annexed to the ſaid Book or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, of <hi>Liberty vindicated againſt Slavery:</hi> 
                           <q>of which Letter, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſeth a paſſage, reflecting in a ſcandalous way upon the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable houſes of Parliament: Of which Book, entituled, <hi>John Whites Defence,</hi>  the ſaid <hi>John White</hi> confeſſeth, and acknowledgeth himſelf to be the Author and Publiſher.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <q>But the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> denied himſelf to be in any ſort the Writer, Contriver, Author, or publiſher of the ſaid other Books, Treatiſe, and Letter, or of any of them; or that he had any hand, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, or approbation, in, or concerning the writing, printing, or publiſhing of the ſame, or any of them.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>"And the ſaid <hi>John White,</hi> did not at our entring into the hearing of the ſaid differences, and matters of controverſie, nor at any time ſince produce or offer unto us any ſufficient proofs, by witneſſes, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: <q>Wherby it did, or might appear unto us, That the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> was the Writer, Contriver, Author, or publiſher of the ſaid Bookes, Letters, and Treatiſe, ſo by him denied as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or of any of them: And the ſaid <hi>John White</hi> being now offered further time to produce his witneſſes, or other good proofs, which he had to inſiſt upon, for the making good of the ſeverall Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in, and by his the ſaid <hi>John Whites</hi> book, laid and fixed upon the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburn;</hi> He the ſaid <hi>Iohn White,</hi> abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to take any further time in that behalf; expreſly ſaying, hee would travell no more in it; We the ſaid Arbitrators, upon due conſideration of the whole premiſes aforeſaid, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>eer of opinion;</q> That the ſaid <hi>Iohn White</hi> (as the ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e hath been, &amp; is repreſented &amp; appearing before us) had no ſufficient ground to write print, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, That the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> was the Writer, or Author of the ſaid Bookes, Treatiſe, and Letter, or any of them: <q>But that the ſaid <hi>Iohn White</hi> in and by his writing, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>inting and publiſhing of his ſaid Book, entituled, <hi>Iohn Whites Defence, &amp;c.</hi> in manner and form as aforeſaid <hi>hath unjuſtly ſcandalized the ſaid L. Col. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>il<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>burn;</hi> And thefore, we the ſaid Arbitrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>s do moſt unanimouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward, That the ſaid <hi>Iohn White</hi> ſhall before the 10. day of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant moneth of <hi>October,</hi> make a publike acknowledgment before Col. <hi>Francis Weſt,</hi> Lieutenant of the ſaid Tower of <hi>London,</hi>
                           </q> at his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:130934:32"/>
the ſaid Lieutenants houſe in the ſaid Tower, <q>That he the ſaid <hi>Iohn White</hi> hath done the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> wrong, and ſhal make and pronounce the ſaid acknowledgment, in theſe words following;</q> That is to ſay, <hi>I Iohn White, one of the Warders of the Tower of London; Do acknowledge, that I have unjuſtly wronged Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Col.</hi> I. Lilburn, <hi>in, and by my writing, and publiſhing in print, in ſuch ſort as I did, That he was the Writer, Author, or Contriver of a Book called,</hi> Liberty vindicated againſt Slavery, <hi>And of a Printed Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereunto annexed; And of a Booke, called,</hi> An Alarum to the Houſe of Lords: <hi>For all which, and for all the unjuſt, and ſcandalous matters and language alleadged, and uſed by me, in my ſaid Booke, refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting upon the ſaid Lieutenant Col.</hi> Lilburn; <hi>I am heartily ſorry.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <q>We the ſaid Arbitrators doe alſo award, That after the ſaid <hi>Iohn <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hite</hi> hath ſo made and pronounced the ſaid acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment before the ſaid Mr. Lieutenant;</q> Hee the ſaid <hi>Iohn White</hi> ſhall then deliver his ſaid acknowledgment in writing (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by him the ſaid <hi>Iohn <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hite</hi>) into the cuſtody of the ſaid <q>Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> to be by him kept and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of, for his better vindication, againſt the ſaid ſcandals ſaid upon him by the ſaid <hi>Iohn White,</hi> in his the ſaid <hi>Iohn <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hites</hi> ſaid Book.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>Laſtly, we the ſaid Arbitrators do award, That this our award ſhall be a finall end of all differences and matters of controverſie <q>whatſoever betwixt the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>I. Lilburn,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Iohn White,</hi> to us, or to our award in any wiſe, ſubmitted by the ſaid parties, from the beginning of the world, unto the day of their ſaid ſubmiſſion to our award;</q> ſo farre as the ſame doth, or may concern the ſaid parties, or either of them in their particulars: and that the ſaid parties from henceforth ſhall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> continue lovers <q>and friends, without any repetition of former injuries on either part.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <q>And for the better clearing of the ſaid <hi>Iohn White</hi> in his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, touching ſome rumours of couzenage, and perjury by him ſuppoſed to be committed, or touching his being forſworn, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcattered abroad to his diſcredit;</q> We the ſaid Arbitrators, do unanimouſly declare; that we have not found any colour, much <q>leſſe any juſt ground to fix upon the ſaid <hi>Iohn VVhite</hi> any ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:130934:32"/>
of, or for the ſame, or any part thereof; But doe thereof in our opinions, abſolutely cleer him.</q> Given under our hands and ſeales the 7. day of <hi>Octob.</hi> aforeſaid, 1646.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Strangwaies.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Lewis Dives,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Glanvill.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>William Morton.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But the Lieutenant not being willing, for cauſes beſt knowne to himſelf, that the ſubmiſſion or recantation, ſhould be made before, or in his preſence; it was done at Lir <hi>John Glanvils</hi> chamber: the Copy of which, thus followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="recantation">
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> John White, one of the Warders of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> Doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that I have unjuſtly wronged <hi>Lieut. Col. Iohn Lilburn,</hi> in, and by my writing, and publiſhing in print, in ſuch ſort as I did; that he was the Writer, Author, or Contriver, of a Booke called, <hi>Liberty vindicated againſt Slavery;</hi> and of a Printed Letter thereunto annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and of a Book or Treatiſe, called, <hi>An Alarum to the Houſe of Lords:</hi> For all which, and for the <hi>unjuſt, and ſcandalous matters and language alleadged, and uſed by me, in my ſaid Book, reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſaid Lieut. Col. Lilburn;</hi> I am heartily ſorry: and in teſtimony thereof, I have hereunto ſubſcribed my hand, the <hi>8.</hi> day of <hi>October, 1646.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>JOHN WHITE.</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Subſcribed, pronounced, and acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted,</hi> 
                              <date>
                                 <hi>the 9. day of</hi> Octob. <hi>1646, in the preſence of us;</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <list>
                                       <head>Knights.</head>
                                       <item>John Strangwaies,</item>
                                       <item>Lewis Dive,</item>
                                       <item>Iohn Glanvill,</item>
                                       <item>William Morton,</item>
                                       <item>Henry Vaughan,</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Chriſtopher Comport, <hi>Warder in the Tower.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:130934:33"/>And now to conclude at the preſent; becauſe there is not any, diſcourſe of mine own abroad in Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (ſince I was firſt locked up ſo cloſe, <hi>as I was by the Lords in Newgate</hi>) by way of Narrative, to ſtate my caſe to the world; I ſhall, it may bee, informe and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, many mens raſh cenſures; by inſerting firſt my Wifes late Petition to the Houſe of Commons; and becauſe by a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Committee to whom my cauſe was referred, it was judged a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>claration, rather then a Petition, and ſo unfit to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon any further, after once reading there: although I am not apt to think, <hi>if I had been a man accuſtomed to write Letters to my Lord Cottington,</hi> when he was at <hi>Oxford</hi> at that time; when by Ordinance of Parliament, it was little leſſe then death ſo to doe, her Petition, and my cauſe, would have found more favour from that Gentleman, then they did, whoſe cavels neceſſitated me to ſend a Petition of my own, to the ſame Committee, which I ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l alſo inſert. But firſt of all, my wifes Petition thus follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:130934:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Choſen and betruſted Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, aſſembled in the high and ſupream Court of PARLIAMENT.</head>
                        <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>ELIZABETH LILBURNE,</hi> wife to Lieu. Col. <hi>JOHN LILBURNE,</hi> who hath been for above eleven weeks by-paſt, moſt unjuſtly divorced from him, by the Houſe of Lords, and their tyrannicall Officers, againſt the Law of <hi>GOD,</hi> and (as ſhe conceives) the law of the Land.</head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THat you only and alone are choſen by the <hi>Commons of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to maintain their Lawes and Liberties, and to do them juſtice and right;<note n="a" place="margin">Coll. of decl: pag. 264. 336. 382, 508, 613. 705. 711. 716, 721, 724, 725, 726, 729. 730.</note> which you have often before <hi>God</hi> and the World <hi>ſworn</hi> to do:<note n="b" place="margin">Coll. decl. page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> proteſtation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> and covena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </note> yea, and in divers of your <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations</hi> declared; it is your duty (in regard of the truſt repoſed in you) ſo to doe;<note n="c" place="margin">Coll. decl. pag. 81<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 262, 266, 267, 340, 459. 462, 471, 473, 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>, 690.</note> without any private aimes, perſonall reſpects, or paſſions whatſoever:<note n="d" place="margin">Col. declar p. 464, 490, 750.</note> And that you think nothing too good to be hazarded in the diſcharge of your conſciences for the obtaining of theſe ends:<note n="e" place="margin">Coll. declar. p. 214. 67.</note> And that you will give up your ſelves to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of your power, and judgement; to maintain truth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your ſelves to the will of God;<note n="f" place="margin">Col. decla. p. 666.</note> which is to doe juſtice and<note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>5.16, 17.</note> right, and ſecure the <hi>Perſons, Eſtates,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of all that joyned with you;<note n="h" place="margin">Col. declar. 666. 673.</note> imprecating the <hi>judgements of heaven</hi> to fall upon you when you decline from theſe ends:<note n="*" place="margin">Col. Declar. 4</note> you judging,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:130934:34"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb facs="tcp:130934:34"/>
                           <pb n="65" facs="tcp:130934:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="66" facs="tcp:130934:36"/>
it the greateſt <hi>ſcandall</hi> that can be laid upon you, that you either doe or intend to <hi>ſubvert the Lawes, Liberties, and Freedoms of the people.</hi>
                           <note n="i" place="margin">Col. decla p 264, 281, 494. 497. 654, 694, 696.</note> Which <hi>Freedoms, &amp;c.</hi> you your ſelves call, <hi>The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Birth-right of Engliſh-men,</hi>
                           <note n="k" place="margin">col. declar. p. 738, 14845.</note> who are born equally free, and to whom the law of the land is an equall inheritance: And therefore your confeſſe in your Declaration of 23. <hi>Octob.</hi> 1642.<note n="l" place="margin">Pag. 660.</note> It is your duty to uſe your beſt endevours, that the meaneſt of the <hi>Commonalty</hi> may enjoy their own <hi>birth-right, freedome and liberty</hi> of the lawes of the land; being <hi>equally</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>intiteld thereunto with the greateſt ſubject,</hi> The knowledge of which, as coming from your own mouthes, and Pen, imboldned your <hi>Petitioner,</hi> with confidence, to make her humble ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe to you, and to put you in mind, that her husband, above 2 mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths agoe, made his formall and legall appeal to you againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and uſurpation of the <hi>Lords</hi> acted upon him; which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, read, committed, and promiſed him juſtice in: But as yet no report is made of his buſines, nor any relief or actuall juſtice holden out unto him; although you have ſince found time to paſſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and pardons, for the infranchiſing of thoſe that your ſelves have declared <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Enemies</hi> to the <hi>kingdome:</hi> which is no ſmall cauſe of ſorrow to your <hi>Petitioner,</hi> and many others, that her h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sband, who hath adventured his life, and all that hee had in the World, in your loweſt condition for you ſhould; bee ſo ſlighted and diſregarded by you, as though you had forgot the duty you owe to the <hi>kingdome,</hi> and your many <hi>Oathes, Vowes,</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi>
                           <note n="**" place="margin">Decl. 460. 498. 666. 673</note> which neglect hath haſtned the almoſt utter ruine of of your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, her husband, and ſmall children. For the <hi>Lords</hi> in a moſt ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall and barbarous manner (being encouraged by your neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect) have ſince committed her husband, for about three weeks, <hi>cloſe priſoner to Newgate,</hi> locked him up in a little room, without the uſe of pen, ink, or paper (for no other cauſe but for refuſing to kneel at the Bar of thoſe, that by Law are none of his Judges.)<note n="m" place="margin">Magna <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>harta 29 Sir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. <hi>Cook</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Inſtit, fol. 28, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>9. Rot. 2. Ed. 3.</note> The cruell Jaylors all that time refuſing to let your Petitioner, or any of his friends, to ſet their, feet over the threſhold of his chamber doore, or to come into the priſon-yard to ſpeak with him, or to deliver un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands, either meat, drink, money, or any other neceſſaries. A moſt barbarous &amp; illegall cruelty! ſo much complained of by your ſelves in your <hi>Petition and Remonſtrance to the King,</hi> 1. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1641.<note n="n" place="margin">col. declar. 6, 7, 8.</note> 
                           <hi>and digeſted and abhorred there,</hi> by you, as <hi>actions and cruelties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:130934:36"/>
more the proper iſſues of Turks, Pagans, Tyrants, and men without any knowledge of God, then of theſe that have the leaſt ſpark of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, Honour, or juſtice in their breaſts.</hi> And then while they thus tyrannized over your Petitioners husband; they command (as your Petitioner is Informed) Mr. <hi>Sergeant Finch,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hearne,</hi> Mr. <hi>Haile,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Glover,</hi> to draw up a charge againſt your Petitioners huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, without giving him the leaſt notice in the world of it, to fit himſelf againſt the day of his <hi>tryall:</hi> but contrary to all law, juſtice, and Conſcience, dealt worſe with him, then ever the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> did; not only in keeping his Lawyers from him, but even all manner of <hi>Councellors</hi> and <hi>Friends</hi> whatſoever, even at that time when they were about to try him: and then of a ſudden ſend a Warrant for him to come to their Bar (who had no legall authority over him) to heare his charge read: where he found the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> his profeſſed enemy, and the onely party (of a Lord) concerned in the buſineſſe; to bee his chiefe Judge, contrary to that juſt Maxime of law, <hi>That no man ought to be both party and judge;</hi> (a practice which the unjuſt <hi>Star-chamber</hi> it ſelfe, in the dayes of its tyranny, did bluſh at, and refuſe to practice, as was often ſeen in the Lord <hi>Coventries caſe,</hi> &amp;c.) And without any regard to the Earle of <hi>Man heſters</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (in your Houſe) of treachery to his Countrey, by Lieu. Gen. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> which is commoely reported to bee punctually and fully proved, and a charge of a higher nature then the Earle of <hi>Straffords,</hi> for which he loſt his head: And which alſo, renders him, ſo long as he ſtands ſo impeached; uncapable in any ſenſe, of being a Iudge. And a great wrong and injuſtice it is unto the <hi>kingdome</hi> to permit him; and to himſelfe, if innocent; not to have had a legall triall ere this, to his juſtification or condemnation. And beſides all this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your <hi>Petitioners husband</hi> ſtood to his apeale, to your <hi>Honours,</hi> and would not betray <hi>Englands liberties;</hi> which you have, all of you, ſworn to preſerve, maintain, and defend: they moſt <hi>arbitra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, illegally,</hi> and <hi>tyrannically,</hi> ſentenced your Petitioners ſaid huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to pay 4000.l. to the King (not to the State) <hi>for ever to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to beare any Office in Church or Common-wealth, either Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall or Civill, and to lie ſeven yeares a priſoner in the extraordinary chargeable priſon of the Tower;</hi> where he is in many particulars ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally dealt withall, as he was, when he was in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now foraſmuch as the <hi>Lords</hi> as they claime<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> themſelves to bee a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:130934:37"/>
                           <hi>Houſe of Peeres</hi> have no legall judgement about Commoners, that your (Petitioner can heare of, but what is expreſſed in the Statute of the 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 5. which are, <hi>delayes of juſtice, or error in judgement in inferior Courts</hi> onely, and that with ſuch limitations and qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as are there expreſſed; which are, that there ſhall be <hi>one Biſhop</hi> at leaſt in the judgment, and an expreſſe <hi>Comiſſion from the King,</hi> for their medling with it. All which was wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting in the caſe of your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners husband, being begun and ended by themſelves alone. And alſo ſeeing that by the 29 of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> your Petitioners husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or any other Commoner whatſoever; in criminall caſes, are not to be tried otherwiſe then by their Peeres: which Sir <hi>Ed. Cook,</hi> in his expoſition of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> (which book is printed by your owne ſpeciall authority) ſaith, is meant [equals] <hi>fol.</hi> 28. <hi>In which,</hi> (ſaith he, fol. 29.) <hi>are compriſed, Knights, Eſquires, Gentlemen, Citizens, Yeomen, and Burgeſſes of ſeverall degrees; but no Lords.</hi> And in p. 46. he ſaith: <hi>No man ſhall be diſſeiſed]</hi> that is, put out of <hi>ſeiſon,</hi> or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed of his <hi>freehold;</hi> that is, (ſaith he) <hi>lands,</hi> or <hi>livelihood, or of his liberties or free cuſtomes,]</hi> that is, of ſuch franchiſes and freedoms, and free cuſtomes as belong to him by his free <hi>Birth-right, unleſſe it be by the lawful judgment</hi> (that is, verdict of his <hi>Equals;</hi> that is (ſaith he) of men of his own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition:] <hi>or by the law of the land;</hi> that is (to ſpeak it once for all) <hi>By the due courſe and proceſſe of law.</hi> And, ſaith he, <q>No man ſhall be in any ſort deſtroyed, unleſſe it be by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and judgment of his Peeres] that is, Equals or by the law of the land. And the Lords themſelves in old time, did truly confeſſe: That for them to give judgement of a Commoner in a criminall caſe, is contrary to law; as is clear by the Parliaments record in the caſe of Sir <hi>Simon d' Bereford.</hi> 4. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 2.</q> the copy of which is now in the hands of Mr. H. <hi>Martin,</hi> &amp; they there record it, <q>That his caſe who was condemned by them for murthering King <hi>Edw.</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. ſhall not bee drawne in future time into preſident, becauſe it was contrary to law, they being not his Peeres, that is, his Equals.</q> And foraſmuch as the manner of their proceedings was contrary to all the former wayes of the law publickly eſtabliſhed by Parliament in this kingdom, as appeares by ſeverall <hi>Statutes</hi>
                           <note n="o" place="margin">5. Ed. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. 25. Ed. 3 4. 28. E. 3. 3. 37. Ed. 3. 8. 38. Ed. 3. 9. 42, Ed. 3. 3. 17. Ri. 2. 6. Rot. parli. 43. E 3. Sir Io: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lees caſe, Num. 21, 22, 23, &amp;c. lib. 10. fol. 74. in caſe delar. marſhalſes, ſee Cook, 2 part Inſtit. fol. 46.</note> which expreſly ſay, <q>That none ſhall be impriſoned, nor put out of his free-hold, nor of his franchiſes, nor free cuſtomes, unleſſe it be by the law of the land, And that none ſhall bee taken by Petition, or ſuggeſtion
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:130934:37"/>
made to the King, or to his Councell, unleſſe it bee by indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or preſentment of good and lawfull people of the ſame neighbourhood where ſuch deeds be done, in due manner, or by proceſſe made, or by Writ originall at the common-law.</q> Which Statutes are nominally and expreſly confirmed by the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> by the <hi>Act made this preſent Parliament for the aboliſhing the Star-chamber;</hi> and thereby, all acts repealed that formerly were made in derogation of them. But contrary hereunto, the Lords (like thoſe wicked <hi>Juſtices</hi> ſpoken of by Sir <hi>Ed. Cook</hi>
                           <note n="p" place="margin">2. Part. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. 51.</note> in ſtead of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her husband by the law of the land; proceed againſt him by a partiall tryall, flowing from their arbitrary will, pleaſure, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, &amp;c.<note n="*" place="margin">Rot. part. 2. 1. H. 4. mem. 2. num. 1.27. Inſtit. f. 51. Book declar. 58. 39. 278. 845.</note> For though they ſummoned him up to their <hi>Barre, June</hi> 10. 1646. to anſwer a <hi>Charge:</hi> yet they refuſed to ſhew it him, or give him a Copy of it, but committed him to <hi>Newgate, June</hi> 11. 1646. (although he behaved himſelfe then with reſpect towards them both in word and geſture), meerly for refuſing to anſwer to their <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition-like Interrogatories,</hi> and for delivering his legall Proteſtation. Their <hi>Mittimus</hi> being as illegall as their ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning of him, and their own proceedings with him. Their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment running, <hi>To be kept there:</hi> not till hee be delivered by due courſe of Law; but, <hi>During their pleaſure:</hi> which Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> ſaith, <hi>is illegall,</hi>
                           <note n="q" place="margin">2. part. inſtit fol. 52, 53.</note> and then locked up cloſe, that ſo hee might bee in an impoſſibility to underſtand how they intended to proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
                        <p>Wherefore your Petitioner humbly prayeth, to grant unto her husband the benefit of the law, and to admit him to your Bar him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to plead his own cauſe, if you be not ſatisfied in the maner of his proceedings, or elſe according to law, juſtice, and that duty &amp; obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation that lieth upon you; forthwith to releaſe him from his unjuſt impriſonment: and to reſtain &amp; prohibit the illegal &amp; arbitrary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the <hi>Lords,</hi> according to that <hi>ſufficient power</hi> enſtated upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, for the enabling you faithfully to diſcharge the truſt repoſed in you, &amp; to vacuate this his <hi>illegal ſentence and fine,</hi> and to give him juſt and honorable reparations from the Lords, &amp; all thoſe that have unjuſtly executed their unjuſt <hi>Commands:</hi> It being <hi>a Rule in law,</hi> and a <hi>Maxime</hi> made uſe of by your ſelves in your <hi>Declaration</hi> 2. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</hi> 1642.<note n="r" place="margin">col declar. 723.</note> 
                           <hi>That the Kings illegall commands, though accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his preſence, doe not excuſe thoſe that obey them;</hi> much leſſe the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:130934:38"/>
Lords, with which the law accordeth, and ſo was reſolved by the Judges, 16. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6.<note n="s" place="margin">See Cook. 2. part. Inſtit. fol. 187.</note> And that you will legally and judicially, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examine the crimes of the <hi>Earle of Mancheſter,</hi> and Col <hi>King,</hi> which the Petitioners husband, and others, have ſo often complained to you of, and doe <hi>exemplary juſtice</hi> upon them, according to their deſerts: or elſe, according to <hi>law</hi> and <hi>juſtice,</hi> puniſh thoſe (if any) that have falſly complained of them.<note n="t" place="margin">3. E. 33. 2. R. 2.5. 37. E. 3. 18. 38. E 39. 12. R. 2. 11. 17. R. 2. 6. 122. p. &amp; M. 3. 1 El. 6.</note> And that you would, without further delay, give us reliefe by doing us juſtice.<note n="v" place="margin">9 H. 3. 29 2. E. 3. 8. 5. E 3. 9. 14. E. 3 14. 11. E. 2. 10.</note> All which, ſhe the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther earneſtly deſiteth, becauſe his impriſonment in the Tower is extraordinary chargeable and inſupportable: although by right, and the cuſtom of that place; his <hi>fees, chamber, and diet, ought to be allowed him, and paid out of the Treaſure of the Crown</hi>) he having waſted &amp; ſpent himſelf with almoſt <hi>ſix years attendance,</hi> and expectation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Honours for juſtice and raparations againſt his barbarous <hi>Sentence, &amp;c.</hi> of the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> to his <hi>extraordinary charge and dammage,</hi> and yet never received a peny; and alſo loſt divers <hi>hundred pounds,</hi> the yeare he was a priſoner in <hi>Oxford Caſtle</hi> for you. Neither can he receive his <hi>Arreares</hi> for (the price of his blood) his faithfull ſervice with the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> although he ſpent with him much of his own money. And the laſt year, by the unadviſed means of ſome <hi>Members</hi> of this <hi>Honorable Houſe,</hi> was committed priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for above 3. moneths, to his extraordinary charges and expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: And yet in concluſion he was releaſt, and to this day knoweth not wherefore he was impriſoned. For which, according to <hi>law</hi> and <hi>juſtice,</hi> he ought to receive reparations; but yet he never had a peny. All which particulars conſidered, doe render the condition of your <hi>Petitioner,</hi> her <hi>husband</hi> and <hi>children,</hi> to be very nigh ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, unleſſe your <hi>ſpeedy</hi> and <hi>long-expected juſtice</hi> prevent the ſame. Which your <hi>Petitioner</hi> doth earneſtly intreat at your hands, as her right, and that which in equity, honour, and conſcience, cannot be denied her.<note n="w" place="margin">col. declar. 127, 174, 244, 253, 282, 284, 285, 312, 313, 321, 322, 467, 490, 514, 516, 520, 521, 532, 533 534, 535, 537, 539, 541, 543, 555, 560.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And as in duty bound, ſhe ſhall ever pray, that your hearts may be kept upright, and thereby enabled timely and faithfully to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the duty you owe to the kingdome, according to the <hi>Great Truſt</hi> repoſed in you: And ſo free your ſelves from giving cauſe to bee judged men that ſeeke your ſelves more then the publick good.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:130934:38"/>
                        <head>To the Honourable, the choſen, betruſted, and repreſentative Body of all the Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> aſſembled.</head>
                        <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> a legall Free-man of <hi>England;</hi> though now unjuſtly impriſoned by the Lords, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary chargeable Priſon of the Tower of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>SHEWETH, THAT</opener>
                        <p>WHereas the Petitioner is a legall and free-born <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> and ought by the fundamentall lawes of this Land, to enjoy the benefit of all the lawes, liberties, priviledges, and immunities of a free-born man, and a Commoner of <hi>England:</hi> and whereas by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realm; no free-man may be taken &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, but by lawfull judgment of his equals, who are men of his own condition, and the Law of the Land: and by the Law of the ſame, no man ought to be impriſoned, before he be taken upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, or preſentment, by good men of the ſame neighbour-hood, or by due proceſſe of Law. And whereas, every man that is taken or impriſoned by the common Lawes of the Land, ought to be bayled: But he that is taken and convicted for Murder or Felony, or for ſome other offence for which a man ought to loſe life or member. And by the Statutes of this Realm, every man is baylable; unleſſe he be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for Treaſon, Murder, Felony, or ſome particular caſe excepted; wherof the Petitioner is no wayes guilty. But your Petitioner ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that he being taken and impriſoned above 4 Moneths, by colour of unjuſt orders, and an illegall ſentence of the Lords pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in their houſe (although they have no legall jurisdiction over him) for ſuppoſed contempts and ſcandals committed againſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:130934:39"/>
them, which was nothing elſe then a defence of his own liberty, and of all the free-men of <hi>England,</hi> in a plea and defence put into the ſaid houſe, which contained an Appeal to your Honours, againſt their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt proceedings: for which ſuppoſed contempts, he is by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſentence committed to the Tower, there to remain for the ſpace of 7. years, and diſabled to bear any office, either Military or Civill, and to pay 4000.l. Fine: All which proceedings of their Lordſhips, the Petitioner doth proteſt againſt as unjuſt, illegall, and deſtructive to the liberties, immunities, and priviledges of all the Commons of <hi>England;</hi> which he doubts not to free himſelf, and all other free-born <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> of, by the Juſtice of this honourable Houſe (to whom he hath formerly, and now alſo doth Appeale) and by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Lawes of this Land.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, your Petitioner doth moſt humbly pray, that he may be inlarged, at leaſt upon bayle, being by Law liable to follow and proſecute his cauſe depending before you, and redemption from the ſaid illegall ſentence, and to obtain juſt and legall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations from the inflictors and executors thereof.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And he ſhall pray, &amp;c.</hi> JOHN LILBURN.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>COurteous Reader,</hi> by reaſon I am prohibited to have Pen, Ink, and Paper; I am forced now to write a peece, and then a peece, and ſcarce have time and opportunity ſeriouſly to peruſe and correct what I write; and in regard I cannot be at the Preſſe, either to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, or reviſe my own lines (which beſides is attended with many difficulties and hazards,) I muſt intreat thee, as thou readeſt, to amend with thy Pen, what in ſence or quotations may be wanting, or falſe; &amp; I ſhal reſt thy true and faithfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Country-man, ready to ſpend my bloud for the fundamentall Lawes and Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> againſt any power what-ever that would deſtroy them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN LILBVRN.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my prerogative, and illegall impriſonment in the Tower of</hi> London, <date>
                     <hi>this preſent</hi> Octob. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:130934:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
